<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[undefined - Dietrich Ayala]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internet freedom, the web and Mozilla.]]></description><link>/</link><generator>Ghost</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2017 14:01:09 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tag/undefined/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Github Project Pages with HTTPS and Custom Domains]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I recently migrated this blog to be served by Github instead of a Digital Ocean droplet. Mostly, this is laziness. I just want one less thing to have to manage. One less thing to worry about. Also, I really wanted to get behind HTTPS and while Sole was kind enough to write up a series on how to use Let&#39;s Encrypt, I just kept putting it off.</p>
<p>So for now, I&#39;ve hosted on Github pages in a project site, using Cloudflare in front for HTTPS. Whether you like Cloudflare or not, this let me at least get a simple zero-management solution to HTTPS hosting of static blog content for now. I can go back to a manually-hosted-and-configured site when I&#39;ve got some free time and self-loathing to spare.</p>
<p>For further reading on threat modeling, and which threat actors are relevant concerns in the various Cloudflare SSL configurations, I really liked this <a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/cloudflare-ssl-and-unhealthy-security-absolutism/">2016 post by Troy Hunt</a>.</p>
<p>Read on to learn how you can set this up for yourself.</p>
<h2 id="step-1-register-your-domain-name">Step 1: Register Your Domain Name</h2>
<p>If you haven&#39;t already done so, register a domain name. I use Namecheap. Never had any problems, and as far as I know <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GoDaddy#Controversies">they&#39;re not assholes</a>.</p>
<p>Use whatever default nameservers are provided. It doesn&#39;t matter since we&#39;ll go back and change them later with the ones that Cloudflare give us.</p>
<h2 id="step-2-configure-github">Step 2: Configure Github</h2>
<p>This tutorial assumes you already have a Github project page that you want to point the domain name at. If you are just getting started, Github has <a href="https://pages.github.com/">extensive documentation</a> on how to do this.</p>
<p>Once you have a Github repo and have your Github Pages site working, go to the Settings tab:</p>
<p>IMG</p>
<p>Scroll down to the Github Pages section and add your domain name in the Custom Domain field and click the &quot;Save&quot; button.</p>
<p>IMG</p>
<h2 id="step-3-set-up-cloudflare">Step 3: Set up Cloudflare</h2>
<p>Go to <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com">Cloudflare.com</a>, create an account, and then <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/a/add-site">add a website</a>.</p>
<p>IMG</p>
<p>Cloudflare will scan your existing DNS settings and then walk you through setting up your website.</p>
<h2 id="step-4-configure-nameservers">Step 4: Configure Nameservers</h2>
]]></description><link>/lazyhttps/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/lazyhttps/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Github]]></category><category><![CDATA[HTTPS]]></category><category><![CDATA[SSL]]></category><category><![CDATA[Cloudflare]]></category><category><![CDATA[HOWTO]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Github+Bugzilla Add-on Updated]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I updated the add-on to either show which bug it&#39;ll add the patch to, or link to the Enter Bug page on Bugzilla. If you choose to create a new bug, the Bugzilla page will open in a new tab.</p>
<p>The &quot;new bug&quot; scenario is still far too bumpy, requiring you to go to a new tab, get the new bug number, go back to the pull request page, update the pull request title, and then reload the page. Maybe in the next version we could put the new bug page in a panel in the current tab, and then automatically submit the attachment after the bug is created?</p>
<p><a href="http://j.mp/dYtZbs">Install</a>.</p>
<p>Screenshot of bug detected:</p>
<p><img src="dPzAy.png" alt="" title="bug detected"></p>
<p>Screenshot of no bug detected:</p>
<p><img src="COQno.png" alt="" title="no bug detected"></p>
]]></description><link>/2011/03/githubbugzilla-add-on-updated/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2011/03/githubbugzilla-add-on-updated/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Add-ons]]></category><category><![CDATA[Bugzilla]]></category><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[Github]]></category><category><![CDATA[jetpack]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2011 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>