<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[undefined - Dietrich Ayala]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internet freedom, the web and Mozilla.]]></description><link>/</link><generator>Ghost</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 23:01:51 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tag/undefined/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Mozlandia - A Portland mini-guide for Mozillians]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Around 1,100 Mozillians will be in Portland next week. WELCOME!</p>
<p>Here is a list of things I recommend that you see, do, eat and drink and some handy tips. I&#39;ve focused on places that are in or near downtown, though included some spots worth going out of your way for.</p>
<p>That said, downtown is not Portland. Well, obviously it&#39;s part of it, duh. But it&#39;s not overly representative of the Portland you&#39;ve heard so much about. Get out of downtown for an evening or afternoon - and check out one of the neighborhoods. Nothing listed here is very far from downtown - Portland is pretty small.</p>
<p>I&#39;ve left a LOT out. And forgot the rest. If you have recommendations, leave them in the comments.</p>
<p>UPDATE: Blue Star donuts, which are far more delicious but far less penis-shaped than Voodoo donuts, will be <a href="http://pdx.eater.com/2014/11/26/7295121/blue-star-donuts-anniversary-free-beignets-expanded-menu">giving away free beignets on Friday Dec 5</a>.</p>
<p>GENERAL TIPS</p>
<ul>
<li>Portland has no Uber or Uber-like services. If you have Car2Go in your city you can use that here too. <a href="http://gocurb.com/">Curb </a>is the app for local taxi service through a couple of providers. You can get a bus to pretty much anywhere without too much of a wait. Ride the MAX and streetcar if you&#39;re headed to areas that they service.</li>
<li>Oregon has no sales tax. Do your Christmas shopping while you&#39;re here.</li>
<li>It gets dark around 16:30 - 17:00, so factor that into any plans for hikes, etc.</li>
<li>If you go into the mountains, check the road conditions to see if you need chains for the car, or if the area is accessible at all.</li>
<li>Go to Powell&#39;s books. Go a few times. Then go back again. Check out the Science Fiction pillar there - how many have you read?</li>
<li>Get high... for a good view of the city: Have a drink at Departures, dinner at Portland City Grill or visit Pittock Mansion for great views of the city. Even driving over the Fremont bridge (Highway 405) provides a spectacular view of downtown, the Willamette River and our many bridges.</li>
<li>There aren&#39;t a ton of restaurants/bars/coffeehouses that can hold large numbers of people. If you break up into groups of four (max), you&#39;ll have a much better time and the servers, chefs, baristas and bartenders will like you for it.</li>
<li>Be patient. Oregon is home to the slow-food movement in America. Regardless if this explains why your coffee took 20 f<em>*</em>ing minutes to make, it&#39;ll make you feel better to think about that. See also the above note about small group sizes to mitigate the waits.</li>
<li><p>Tipping: I tip a dollar for a good coffee. I generally tip ~20% for any kind of sit-down meal. But I also worked as a barista, server and chef before getting into tech, so I&#39;m biased towards tipping ;)
CARTS - Just the 9th &amp; Alder pod for the purposes of this post. If you&#39;re from California - up here they are not &quot;food trucks&quot;, they are &quot;food carts&quot;... even when they are trucks.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Hoang&#39;s - Get soup #17.</p>
</li>
<li>Nong&#39;s khao man gai - Simple and good and oddly famous.</li>
<li>Wolf &amp; Bear - Israeli street food that is amazing. And vegan.</li>
<li>Güero - Excellent tortas. Add an egg.</li>
<li>La Jarochita 2 - Great Mexican cart. The only Mexican cart (aside from Güero) worth going to at the 9th and Alder cart pod.</li>
<li>Brunch Box - A cart that graduated to a proper storefront, but is right by the 9th and Alder carts. Great egg sandwiches for breakfast (try the Black and Blue) and terribly good burgers the rest of time. Very fast.</li>
<li><p>Kargi Gogo - Georgian food. The country, not the American state. Irakli says it&#39;s legit too.
DRINK</p>
</li>
<li><p>Multnomah Whiskey Library</p>
</li>
<li>Clyde Common</li>
<li>Pepe le Moko</li>
<li>Teardrop</li>
<li><p>Bailey&#39;s Taproom
COFFEE</p>
</li>
<li><p>Courier - They also make fresh canneles daily.</p>
</li>
<li>Heart - Excellent coffee.</li>
<li>Barista</li>
<li>Coffeehouse Northwest</li>
<li>Stumptown</li>
<li>Case Study</li>
<li>Coava - Not downtown but my favorite coffee roaster in town.</li>
<li><p>Ristretto - Not downtown, but fantastic coffee in beautiful spaces. The Nicolai location is especially great - check out the custom metalwork and crazy woodwork, and visit Schoolhouse Electric in the same space.
EAT - I&#39;ve only noted a few of my go-to places, or those that are near where Mozillians are staying, or open late, etc. I&#39;ve got a <a href="https://www.evernote.com/shard/s1/sh/054ed2b6-227a-4934-aaf5-afaeff3f09e6/8b18f677e359bdd1823ec784dc22bfb1">somewhat-up-to-date list here</a> with more recommendations, but there&#39;s just really too much to cover. Go out and explore.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Clyde Common - Always interesting menu, good whiskey selection, great cocktails. Fries + harissa and a cocktail is a great way to end your day and start your evening.</p>
</li>
<li>Tasty and Alder (downtown) - Shared plates, everything is good.</li>
<li>Luc Lac - Vietnamese + cocktails, serves food VERY late, and closest place worth going to that&#39;s also near the Waterfront Marriot.</li>
<li>Bunk - Excellent sandwiches.</li>
<li>Lardo - Excellent sandwiches as well.</li>
<li>Racion - Amazing cocktails and fun Spanish-tinged molecular gastronomy.</li>
<li>Little Big Burger - Fast and good late night burger.</li>
<li><p>Not downtown, but places I always want to go back to...</p>
<ul>
<li>Biwa - Izakaya, open late, always amazing. Burger served only after 11pm.</li>
<li>Tarad - Northern Thai food, open late. Pok Pok gets all the attention but after living in northern Thailand, this is where we go for the real thing.</li>
<li>Mee Sen - Another good Northern Thai food spot we go to.</li>
<li>Podnah&#39;s BBQ - Worth heading up into NE Portland for.</li>
<li>La Taq - Next door to Podnah&#39;s, fantastic Mexican bar food.</li>
<li>Sweedeedee - Most likely to feel like you&#39;re in Portlandia at this spot. Amazing house-baked breads. Tiny. Expect a long wait but good people watching and excellent food.</li>
<li>Por Que No (Mississippi location) - Great tacos.</li>
<li>Ha &amp; VL - Get the special soup of the day, whatever it is.
NEIGHBORHOODS - Places to walk, eat, drink, shop and experience parts of Portland that are far more interesting than downtown.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Alberta St - <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Portland,+OR+97211/@45.559091,-122.649713,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m2!3m1!1s0x5495a71f16982601:0xcfb5dec4cb0cc592">Between NE 15th Ave and NE 31st Ave</a></p>
</li>
<li>Belmont St - A few blocks on either side of <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Portland,+OR+97214/@45.5164534,-122.6295558,18z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m2!3m1!1s0x5495a093801c7a69:0x3044c74094029fc5">SE Belmont and SE 34th</a></li>
<li>Division St - Between <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Portland,+OR+97202/@45.5048033,-122.634579,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m2!3m1!1s0x5495a08423947f4d:0x94ab9ca89f536476">SE 30th and SE 39th</a></li>
<li>East Burnside - From <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Portland,+OR+97214/@45.5117972,-122.6233484,16z/data=!4m2!3m1!1s0x5495a08d8c6660a1:0x65c0bc7bcfa0bfa8">NE Grand Ave to NE 12th Ave</a> and then up and down <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Portland,+OR+97214/@45.5228888,-122.6372625,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m2!3m1!1s0x5495a0bf1c10f7e1:0xc2712506ca1f815c">NE 28th and Burnside</a></li>
<li>Hawthorne Blvd - Between <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Portland,+OR+97214/@45.5117972,-122.6233484,16z/data=!4m2!3m1!1s0x5495a08d8c6660a1:0x65c0bc7bcfa0bfa8">SE 32nd Ave and SE 49th Ave</a></li>
<li>N Mississippi Ave - Between <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Portland,+OR+97227/@45.5478202,-122.675562,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m2!3m1!1s0x5495a74217de3b6b:0xa592780957a53110">N Fremont Ave and N Skidmore Ave</a></li>
<li>NW 23rd Ave - Between <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Portland,+OR+97210/@45.5262249,-122.6984709,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m2!3m1!1s0x549509f13449968b:0x73b4e9cf1403cc8c">W Burnside and NW Thurman Ave</a></li>
<li><p>NE Williams Ave - Between <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Portland,+OR+97212/@45.5507983,-122.6667064,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m2!3m1!1s0x5495a73fc02c7eaf:0x471d67f545f071aa">NE Fremont Ave and NE Skidmore Ave</a>
EXCURSIONS</p>
</li>
<li><p>Columbia Gorge - See Multnomah Falls, the view from Vista House, climb Beacon Rock, stop at the Bonneville Dam and see Herman the Sturgeon, drive across the Bridge of the Gods (and back), then go for lunch at one of the Hood River breweries. Some easy/moderate 1-2 hour hikes I like: Angel&#39;s Rest, the Multnomah/Wahkeena Falls loop, Triple Falls,  Horsetail Falls, Punchbowl Falls, <a href="http://www.portlandhikersfieldguide.org/wiki/Columbia_River_Gorge_Hikes">all listed here</a>.</p>
</li>
<li>Mount Hood - Drive out Highway 26 to the historic Timberline Lodge with amazing views of Mt Hood (if it&#39;s clear), then down to Hood River and head home through the Columbia Gorge on Hwy 84.</li>
<li>Mount St Helens - A couple of hours north, but the view of the blast zone and crater from the visitor center on the NW side is well worth it if the view is clear. On the SE side you can hike one mile underground through Ape Cave, and check out the amazing rock formations and brave the cable bridge at Lava Canyon.</li>
<li>Oregon Coast - About two hours drive. Walk the promenade at Seaside, get ice cream at Tillamook, watch storms from the tip of Oregon at the mouth of the Columbia river.</li>
</ul>
]]></description><link>/2014/11/mozlandia-a-portland-mini-guide-for-mozillians/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2014/11/mozlandia-a-portland-mini-guide-for-mozillians/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozlandia]]></category><category><![CDATA[pdx]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Portland Firefox Developers Meetup]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>One of the cool folks I met at <a href="http://barcampportland.org">BarCampPortland 3</a> was <a href="http://twitter.com/stechz">Benjamin Stover</a>. He works at <a href="http://vidoop.com/">Vidoop</a>, and is the developer of <a href="http://ineedtoreadthis.com/">ineedtoreadthis.com</a>. We were talking at BarCamp about how there&#39;s a lot of Firefox extension development going on, but usually by lone individuals. For instance, many of the extension developers I interact with say the same thing: &quot;Yeah, I&#39;m <em>the</em> person at my company who&#39;s in charge of the extension&quot;. And while there&#39;s a lot of great online resources for extension developers, there&#39;s no local group or meet-up specific to development using the Mozilla platform.</p>
<p>Hence the PDX Firefox Developers Group! If you&#39;re interested in developing Firefox extensions, or hacking Firefox itself, or are already doing so, come out and meet others doing the same. For the first meeting, Ben is going to talk about his <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/pdx-firefox-dev/msg/40b71d5ab74c0db9">unit test framework for extensions</a>, and I&#39;m going to talk about <a href="http://ubiquity.mozilla.com/">Ubiquity</a>, a Mozilla Labs project. I&#39;d like it to be more focused on the hacking than lecturing, so bring your laptop! For example, I&#39;ll walk through the process of writing a new Ubiquity command. Join the <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/pdx-firefox-dev">PDX-Firefox-Dev Google group</a> for ongoing talk about Firefox and Mozilla hacking, or if you have topics you&#39;d like to talk about at the meet-ups.</p>
<p>The group is meeting on the second Wednesday of the month. The first meeting is next Wednesday, May 13th, and is taking place at <a href="http://www.nedspace.com/">Nedspace</a> (directions below) at 7pm. We&#39;ll probably roll somewhere near for drinks afterwards. Please <a href="http://upcoming.yahoo.com/event/2620820/">RSVP on Upcoming</a>.</p>
<p>Portland Firefox Developers Group, May 13 at 7pm at Nedspace</p>
<p>[googlemaps <a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=920+SW+Third+Portland,+OR+92704&amp;sll=45.518828,-122.675681&amp;sspn=0.01747,0.038624&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;t=h&amp;z=14&amp;iwloc=A&amp;ll=45.525352,-122.671967&amp;output=embed&amp;w=425&amp;h=350">http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=920+SW+Third+Portland,+OR+92704&amp;sll=45.518828,-122.675681&amp;sspn=0.01747,0.038624&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;t=h&amp;z=14&amp;iwloc=A&amp;ll=45.525352,-122.671967&amp;output=embed&amp;w=425&amp;h=350</a>]</p>
]]></description><link>/2009/05/portland-firefox-developers-meetup/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2009/05/portland-firefox-developers-meetup/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[meetup]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2009 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Portland Firefox Developers Meetup]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>One of the cool folks I met at <a href="http://barcampportland.org">BarCampPortland 3</a> was <a href="http://twitter.com/stechz">Benjamin Stover</a>. He works at <a href="http://vidoop.com/">Vidoop</a>, and is the developer of <a href="http://ineedtoreadthis.com/">ineedtoreadthis.com</a>. We were talking at BarCamp about how there&#39;s a lot of Firefox extension development going on, but usually by lone individuals. For instance, many of the extension developers I interact with say the same thing: &quot;Yeah, I&#39;m <em>the</em> person at my company who&#39;s in charge of the extension&quot;. And while there&#39;s a lot of great online resources for extension developers, there&#39;s no local group or meet-up specific to development using the Mozilla platform.</p>
<p>Hence the PDX Firefox Developers Group! If you&#39;re interested in developing Firefox extensions, or hacking Firefox itself, or are already doing so, come out and meet others doing the same. For the first meeting, Ben is going to talk about his <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/pdx-firefox-dev/msg/40b71d5ab74c0db9">unit test framework for extensions</a>, and I&#39;m going to talk about <a href="http://ubiquity.mozilla.com/">Ubiquity</a>, a Mozilla Labs project. I&#39;d like it to be more focused on the hacking than lecturing, so bring your laptop! For example, I&#39;ll walk through the process of writing a new Ubiquity command. Join the <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/pdx-firefox-dev">PDX-Firefox-Dev Google group</a> for ongoing talk about Firefox and Mozilla hacking, or if you have topics you&#39;d like to talk about at the meet-ups.</p>
<p>The group is meeting on the second Wednesday of the month. The first meeting is next Wednesday, May 13th, and is taking place at <a href="http://www.nedspace.com/">Nedspace</a> (directions below) at 7pm. We&#39;ll probably roll somewhere near for drinks afterwards. Please <a href="http://upcoming.yahoo.com/event/2620820/">RSVP on Upcoming</a>.</p>
<p>Portland Firefox Developers Group, May 13 at 7pm at Nedspace</p>
<p>[googlemaps <a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=920+SW+Third+Portland,+OR+92704&amp;sll=45.518828,-122.675681&amp;sspn=0.01747,0.038624&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;t=h&amp;z=14&amp;iwloc=A&amp;ll=45.525352,-122.671967&amp;output=embed&amp;w=425&amp;h=350">http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=920+SW+Third+Portland,+OR+92704&amp;sll=45.518828,-122.675681&amp;sspn=0.01747,0.038624&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;t=h&amp;z=14&amp;iwloc=A&amp;ll=45.525352,-122.671967&amp;output=embed&amp;w=425&amp;h=350</a>]</p>
]]></description><link>/2009/05/portland-firefox-developers-meetup/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2009/05/portland-firefox-developers-meetup/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[meetup]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2009 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Beast 7/16/08]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>We finally made it to <a href="http://www.beastpdx.com/" title="Beast">Beast</a>. Overall, a fantastic experience. I would go back in a heartbeat, if only my heart (and wallet) could take that kind of a beating regularly.</p>
<p>Soup</p>
<p>The soup was cucumber and creme fraiche, was airy and cool; some citrus high notes with the cucumber keeping things steady. The flower petals were a beautiful contrast. The chili oil was... missing. Others said they could taste it, but I couldn&#39;t. It would&#39;ve provided perfect dissonance, as well as a textural anchor on the tongue, so my <em>hunch</em> is that it was intended to be drizzled on top, but was forgotten. It was paired with a Gruner Veltliner, worked fine.</p>
<p>Charcuterie</p>
<p>Foie gras bon-bon: Unbelievable on the tongue, but a bit too worshipful. I come from peasant stock, and wanted to eat this on some country bread.</p>
<p>Steak tartare and quail egg on toast: Undoubtedly a highlight of the meal. The tartare was supremely cold with maybe some... scallion and white pepper? I had a minor yolk-splosion, so best to take it all in one bite.</p>
<p>Pork Rillette and house cracker: High expections went unmet. The pork was unnassuming, and the cracker could&#39;ve been crisper.</p>
<p>Duck, duck liver, cherry and pistachio pate: A nice blend of creamy and roasty. I&#39;m just not a fan of mixing fruit, nuts <em>and</em> meat, so it wasn&#39;t my favorite. Also, my less-than-blue blood again was begging for bread or a cracker.</p>
<p>There was also a cornichon on a daub of dijon mustard, a crisp &quot;ice leaf&quot; (IIRC) on a sliced pea salad, and a salami.</p>
<p>All of this was paired with Tessier Cheverny Blanc - wonderful choice: front of the tongue, spicy, light.<em> </em></p>
<p>Entree</p>
<p>The  seared duck breast, alongside a cherry and tomato salsa and pan-fried squash blossoms. The duck was fairly unadorned, which was a great move given it&#39;s place in the courses - nice to focus on purity after the charcuterie carnival. The salsa was more of a salad: Rainier cherries and cherry tomatoes halved and in a mild vinegar. It stood up for itself next to the duck.</p>
<p>The only downer of the course was the Grosbois Vielles Chinon that was the paired with it. Maybe they intentionally chose a wine that would get out of the way... or maybe it was just unremarkable. The duck cried out for a saltier, earthy red - I&#39;d have chosen a tempranillo maybe.</p>
<p>Salad</p>
<p>Oddly, this was the simplest part of the meal, yet all agreed that it vied for a top spot among the courses. It was some local greens and a few peach slices in a sherry vinaigrette. There were marcona almonds, but as they were whole, they were bystanders. The upstaging of the course was the shaved goat cheese. The shameless creamy sourness of goat cheese, perfectly distributed via micro-shavings, hooked up with the sherry, and ravished those damn greens. Playing the excited voyeur was the  Salomon Kogl Riesling - light on the tongue and a nice balance to the piquancy of the sherry.</p>
<p>Cheese</p>
<p>Steve&#39;s cheese - one slice each of a sheep, goat and cow cheese, with poached apricots, candied hazelnuts, saffron shortbread and local honeycomb. The sheep&#39;s cheese stood out - with a broad nuttiness, definitely was the best choice to contrast the preceding course. The shortbread were little buttons, well-sized to reign in the saffron&#39;s tendency to dominate. The honeycomb was what really took this course over the edge, into the realm of culinary primality - a chthonic offering spilt on the civilized craftsmanship of the cheeses.</p>
<p>The Prieler pinot blanc was well paired, provided respite for an overstimulated palate.</p>
<p>Dessert</p>
<p>Lemon verbena meringues with buttermilk ice cream and tayberries and blackberries. The meringue was truly enjoyable, bright and sweet. The wine pairing was JJ Christoffel Urziger Wurzgarten Auslese, and was far too thickly sweet to be served with buttermilk ice cream. We were offered coffee, which was the right choice for this course... but then left us with wine and coffee at the same time, which was awkward.</p>
<p>Tips: The portions were perfect, and the progression of courses was well thought out, so I&#39;d recommend going for all six courses. The wine pairing, with a couple of exceptions, was smart, so I recommend that as well. Go for the second seating, as you&#39;ll get more time to linger.</p>
]]></description><link>/2008/07/beast-71608/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2008/07/beast-71608/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Food]]></category><category><![CDATA[Food]]></category><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><category><![CDATA[restaurants]]></category><category><![CDATA[reviews]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2008 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Beast 7/16/08]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>We finally made it to <a href="http://www.beastpdx.com/" title="Beast">Beast</a>. Overall, a fantastic experience. I would go back in a heartbeat, if only my heart (and wallet) could take that kind of a beating regularly.</p>
<p>Soup</p>
<p>The soup was cucumber and creme fraiche, was airy and cool; some citrus high notes with the cucumber keeping things steady. The flower petals were a beautiful contrast. The chili oil was... missing. Others said they could taste it, but I couldn&#39;t. It would&#39;ve provided perfect dissonance, as well as a textural anchor on the tongue, so my <em>hunch</em> is that it was intended to be drizzled on top, but was forgotten. It was paired with a Gruner Veltliner, worked fine.</p>
<p>Charcuterie</p>
<p>Foie gras bon-bon: Unbelievable on the tongue, but a bit too worshipful. I come from peasant stock, and wanted to eat this on some country bread.</p>
<p>Steak tartare and quail egg on toast: Undoubtedly a highlight of the meal. The tartare was supremely cold with maybe some... scallion and white pepper? I had a minor yolk-splosion, so best to take it all in one bite.</p>
<p>Pork Rillette and house cracker: High expections went unmet. The pork was unnassuming, and the cracker could&#39;ve been crisper.</p>
<p>Duck, duck liver, cherry and pistachio pate: A nice blend of creamy and roasty. I&#39;m just not a fan of mixing fruit, nuts <em>and</em> meat, so it wasn&#39;t my favorite. Also, my less-than-blue blood again was begging for bread or a cracker.</p>
<p>There was also a cornichon on a daub of dijon mustard, a crisp &quot;ice leaf&quot; (IIRC) on a sliced pea salad, and a salami.</p>
<p>All of this was paired with Tessier Cheverny Blanc - wonderful choice: front of the tongue, spicy, light.<em> </em></p>
<p>Entree</p>
<p>The  seared duck breast, alongside a cherry and tomato salsa and pan-fried squash blossoms. The duck was fairly unadorned, which was a great move given it&#39;s place in the courses - nice to focus on purity after the charcuterie carnival. The salsa was more of a salad: Rainier cherries and cherry tomatoes halved and in a mild vinegar. It stood up for itself next to the duck.</p>
<p>The only downer of the course was the Grosbois Vielles Chinon that was the paired with it. Maybe they intentionally chose a wine that would get out of the way... or maybe it was just unremarkable. The duck cried out for a saltier, earthy red - I&#39;d have chosen a tempranillo maybe.</p>
<p>Salad</p>
<p>Oddly, this was the simplest part of the meal, yet all agreed that it vied for a top spot among the courses. It was some local greens and a few peach slices in a sherry vinaigrette. There were marcona almonds, but as they were whole, they were bystanders. The upstaging of the course was the shaved goat cheese. The shameless creamy sourness of goat cheese, perfectly distributed via micro-shavings, hooked up with the sherry, and ravished those damn greens. Playing the excited voyeur was the  Salomon Kogl Riesling - light on the tongue and a nice balance to the piquancy of the sherry.</p>
<p>Cheese</p>
<p>Steve&#39;s cheese - one slice each of a sheep, goat and cow cheese, with poached apricots, candied hazelnuts, saffron shortbread and local honeycomb. The sheep&#39;s cheese stood out - with a broad nuttiness, definitely was the best choice to contrast the preceding course. The shortbread were little buttons, well-sized to reign in the saffron&#39;s tendency to dominate. The honeycomb was what really took this course over the edge, into the realm of culinary primality - a chthonic offering spilt on the civilized craftsmanship of the cheeses.</p>
<p>The Prieler pinot blanc was well paired, provided respite for an overstimulated palate.</p>
<p>Dessert</p>
<p>Lemon verbena meringues with buttermilk ice cream and tayberries and blackberries. The meringue was truly enjoyable, bright and sweet. The wine pairing was JJ Christoffel Urziger Wurzgarten Auslese, and was far too thickly sweet to be served with buttermilk ice cream. We were offered coffee, which was the right choice for this course... but then left us with wine and coffee at the same time, which was awkward.</p>
<p>Tips: The portions were perfect, and the progression of courses was well thought out, so I&#39;d recommend going for all six courses. The wine pairing, with a couple of exceptions, was smart, so I recommend that as well. Go for the second seating, as you&#39;ll get more time to linger.</p>
]]></description><link>/2008/07/beast-71608/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2008/07/beast-71608/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Food]]></category><category><![CDATA[Food]]></category><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><category><![CDATA[restaurants]]></category><category><![CDATA[reviews]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2008 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Firefox 3 Talk at Portland Web Innovators]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.pdxwi.com/">Portland Web Innovators</a> is a monthly meeting of web designers and developers in Portland, Oregon. One of the founders, <a href="http://www.adamduvander.com/">Adam Duvander</a> (of <a href="http://www.bestplaces.net/">Best Places</a> and <a href="http://www.wifipdx.com/">WifiPDX</a>), invited me to come speak about <a href="http://wiki.mozilla.org/Firefox3">Firefox 3</a>. I was told that the turnout was 3x normal, which was cool. <a href="http://www.isitedesign.com/">iSite Design</a> provided the venue, and the pizza, thanks y&#39;all :)</p>
<p>My <a href="http://dietrich.ganx4.com/mozilla/Fx3-WebInnovators.pdf">hastily-made presentation</a> is basically an overview of the user-facing features planned for Fx3 (with Schrep&#39;s #&#39;s slide thrown in to end on). Here are some impressions and take-aways:</p>
<ul>
<li>The group is mostly designers and web developers from small (1 person) to medium (40 people) sized companies. There were some independent contractors, and a few other people from various software/web-related fields.</li>
<li>People seemed generally interested in the &quot;information management&quot; stuff: places, microformats, content handling.</li>
<li>Significant crowd reaction when i said we&#39;d fix the &quot;save password only <em>after</em> a successful logon&quot; bug :)</li>
<li>Unsurprisingly, there was concern about how many new features there were. Several people asked whether the new features would be able to turned off entirely. Questions about whether &quot;the old simpler Firefox&quot; would still be available.</li>
<li>Also unsurprising was the general concern about performance and memory usage.</li>
<li>People were curious about developing both Firefox extensions and XULRunner apps.</li>
</ul>
<p>I might do a follow-up presentation on Fx3 for Developers.
<a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1014"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1016"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1017"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1018"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=102"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1023"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1029"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=103"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1031"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1034"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1035"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1036"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1037"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1038"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1039"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=104"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1043"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1045"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1046"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1047"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1048"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1049"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=105"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1050"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1053"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1054"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1055"> </a></p>
]]></description><link>/2007/04/firefox-3-talk-at-portland-web-innovators/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/04/firefox-3-talk-at-portland-web-innovators/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Thermals @ Crystal Ballroom]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>We went to see <a href="http://www.subpop.com/artists/the_thermals">The Thermals</a> last night. First time at the <a href="http://www.mcmenamins.com/index.php?loc=2&amp;category=Location%20Homepage">Crystal Ballroom</a>, in downtown Portland. It&#39;s a <a href="http://www.mcmenamins.com/">McMenamins</a> joint, and as to be expected it was a beautiful old space, renovated and covered with faux-hippie murals. The floor of the place is springy, kinda like gymnastics flooring, brilliant idea.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.teaforjulie.net/">
Tea for Julie</a> was on we got there. Hey guys, get a new band name.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.starsoftrackandfield.com/">Stars of Track and Field</a> were next. Wow I had no idea that you could have so many crescendos in a single song! Hey guys, it kinda detracts from the suspense WHEN THERE IS NONE. I believe this kind of music is known as &quot;anthemo&quot; (a-nth-ee-mo). They were interestingly derivative: The guitar had shades of 70s rock, U2, The Church. The vocals had a bit of Galaxy 500, and someone else that I haven&#39;t quite pinpointed yet. Sometimes they&#39;d bust out the cheesy drum machine and keyboard for some serious Postal Service rip-off action. Ok, I know it sounds like I hated them, but I actually really enjoyed some of the songs (especially those without the keyboard). Definitely talented guys... just haven&#39;t figured out who they want to sound like yet.</p>
<p>After an awesomely short wait (no pretension here!) The Thermals came on. Great show, as to be expected. However, the sound was not so hot, bad acoustics seemed to eat up the guitar punch. We saw them at the Wonder Ballroom (Portland&#39;s got lots of ballrooms it seems) last fall, and the sound there was much better.</p>
<p>The best part of the show though, was watching my daughter totally lose it when the Thermals played; she was head-banging throughout their set. Afterwards she was disappointed that &quot;it was so boring where we were&quot;. We were about 10 feet from the stage, the mosh pit was a few feet to the right, and some guy next to us was carried off basically unconscious from a blow to the head (due to a falling crowd-surfer). An explanation of basic mosh pit arithmetic ensued: falling 250 pound punker + 70 pound 11 year-old = emergency-room trip.</p>
<p>Maybe when you grow another few inches :)</p>
]]></description><link>/2007/02/thermals-crystal-ballroom/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/02/thermals-crystal-ballroom/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[music]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[You are under surveillance.]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Last night we went to a panel discussion on the Bush administration&#39;s warrant-less wiretapping program, at <a href="http://www.pdx.edu/">PSU</a> in downtown Portland. It was put on by the <a href="http://www.nwcrc.org/">NWCRC</a> and <a href="http://www.pfaw.org/pfaw/general/">PFAW</a>, and featured a professor/lawyer, a lawyer handling a case against the government over warrant-less wiretapping, and an activist.</p>
<p>It was f*ckin&#39; scary.</p>
<p>But it was also extremely interesting, and at times even funny. It&#39;s inspiring and humbling to see these smart and talented people out there fighting our government&#39;s encroachments on our rights, on a daily basis. And it&#39;s uplifting to see that it&#39;s possible to keep a sense of humor while doing it... because if we can no longer laugh, then the fascists have truly won.</p>
<p>Yes, you are under surveillance.</p>
<p><strong>DANCE!</strong></p>
]]></description><link>/2006/10/you-are-under-surveillance/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2006/10/you-are-under-surveillance/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[assholes]]></category><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[political]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2006 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Wife on the Telly, Kicking Ass and Taking Names]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>My wife <a href="http://www.girlwrites.com">Shauna</a> just started a fellowship at the <a href="http://www.nwcrc.org/">Northwest Constitutional Rights Center</a> as an attorney. During her first week on the job, there was an <a href="http://portland.indymedia.org/en/2006/10/347085.shtml">anti-Bush protest in downtown Portland</a>, that unfortunately turned violent when a group of protesters went off-route and were turned back by police, using pepper spray, rubber bullets and horses. Shauna was on one of the local news channels that night, giving the NWCRC&#39;s comment on what happened:</p>
<p><a href="http://dietrich.ganx4.com/movies/portland-protest-k2-coverage-10-5-06.mp4">Watch video</a> (6mb MPEG4)</p>
]]></description><link>/2006/10/wife-on-the-telly-kicking-ass-and-taking-names/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2006/10/wife-on-the-telly-kicking-ass-and-taking-names/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[political]]></category><category><![CDATA[politics]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><category><![CDATA[Videos]]></category><category><![CDATA[war]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2006 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mini-review: The Albina Press, North Portland (another coffeehouse)]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Great atmosphere, lots of places to sit inside and out. Sweet treats and Beta Band beats. Located a bit north of the main Mississippi area. It&#39;s east of Interstate 5, but the area seems to be referred to as North Portland, not Northeast.</p>
<ul>
<li>Wi-fi: free</li>
<li>Coffee: Stumptown</li>
<li>Food: cookies, scones, bagels</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;hl=en&amp;q=4637+N.+Albina+Ave,+portland+OR&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;om=1">Map</a></p>
]]></description><link>/2006/08/mini-review-the-albina-press-north-portland-another-coffeehouse/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2006/08/mini-review-the-albina-press-north-portland-another-coffeehouse/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[coffee]]></category><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><category><![CDATA[reviews]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2006 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mini-review: Northstar Coffeehouse, North Portland]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Good atmosphere, but small. Located off Interstate, one block north of Lombard, so it&#39;s pretty far out there, but accessible if you&#39;re stuck up in NOPO. It&#39;s right off the MAX line, and one block from the Fred Meyer.</p>
<ul>
<li>Wi-fi: free</li>
<li>Coffee: Stumptown</li>
<li>Food: quality baked goods, bagels</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;hl=en&amp;q=7540+N.+Interstate,+Portland+OR&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;om=1">Map</a></p>
]]></description><link>/2006/08/mini-review-northstar-coffeehouse-north-portland/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2006/08/mini-review-northstar-coffeehouse-north-portland/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[coffee]]></category><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><category><![CDATA[reviews]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2006 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>