<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[undefined - Dietrich Ayala]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internet freedom, the web and Mozilla.]]></description><link>/</link><generator>Ghost</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2017 08:46:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tag/undefined/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Some Notes on Living in Chiang Mai, Thailand]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Several people have asked me about living in Thailand. After spending a year in Chiang Mai, here are a few suggestions, recommendations and things I wished I knew ahead of time.</p>
<ul>
<li>Learn to speak Thai, at least a little bit. We took classes over Skype video for 2 months from <a href="http://j.mp/yOzhlU">Brett Whiteside</a> and it really helped. I can speak and understand enough basics for cordial and respectful interactions with people, and to eat wherever I want :). If you&#39;re going to be there for a while learn to read Thai. It&#39;s seriously worth it, if only for reading menus and signs.</li>
<li>Always print a detailed map of wherever you&#39;re going. Anywhere. All the time. Really.</li>
<li>Make a custom Google map with the locations of: post office, utility offices (power, water), telco, police station, etc. Just in case.</li>
<li>Banking: ATMs cost US$5 per transaction, and result in currency conversion fees. Instead, open a Bangkok Bank account and get a debit card. Getting a bank account took some paperwork, about an hour of waiting in the bank, and I think you have to pay a small fee. Bangkok Bank is the only Thai bank with a US branch (in NY). This means that you can make direct transfers from US banks to your Bangkok Bank account, allowing for money access with a minimum of delay and fees.</li>
<li>3G: I used AIS, which has unlimited (5GB IIRC) 3G monthly pre-paid option. Absolutely recommended for access to Google Maps while lost ;).</li>
<li>Thai street food is often safer than food from &quot;western&quot; places. The food at the carts is usually bought fresh that day, and is cooked in front of you. The food at &quot;western&quot; hotels and restaurants is cooked out of sight, and they try to store food, which is risky since there&#39;s not really health department inspections like in the states, to ensure the storage is properly done. You&#39;ll find infinite opinions about this - this is my personal experience. There&#39;s no magic solution. You will have some intestinal discomfort at some point.</li>
<li>Western toilets are everywhere. At some point however, you&#39;ll need to use a squat toilet. Chiang Mai Rock Climbing Adventures has humorous yet informative <a href="http://j.mp/yCCD85">instructions for properly using a squat toilet</a>.</li>
<li>Use Foursquare or some other check-in service. I often couldn&#39;t find a place that I wanted to return to, or had forgotten the street, etc.</li>
<li>7-11. Is awesome. In Thailand you will pay your utility bills, refill your phone minutes, purchase concert tickets, and many other things there.</li>
<li>Temples: Wear long pants and shirts with sleeves. Be quiet and respectful. Donate money to them.
Most importantly: Go anywhere and everywhere. Always take a different route. Pull over often. Walk down unfamiliar streets. See every temple. Explore every market. And always <a href="http://j.mp/xJiimy">carry your camera</a>.</li>
</ul>
]]></description><link>/2012/01/some-notes-on-living-in-chiang-mai-thailand/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2012/01/some-notes-on-living-in-chiang-mai-thailand/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[chiang]]></category><category><![CDATA[mai]]></category><category><![CDATA[thailand]]></category><category><![CDATA[travel]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2012 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>