<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[undefined - Dietrich Ayala]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internet freedom, the web and Mozilla.]]></description><link>/</link><generator>Ghost</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2018 19:46:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tag/undefined/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Brussels: Warm Hospitality Amidst Inhuman Conditions]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>We&#39;re at the end of our Performance work-week here in Brussels, and gearing up for a two-day orgy of European open-source culture at FOSDEM. I&#39;ve successfully acquired a cold (and hopefully not worse) due to the temperature being <a href="http://j.mp/xUY8FQ">consistently below freezing</a>.</p>
<p>However, the people here in Brussels have made up for their weather shortcomings by welcoming us wherever we go. Between the hackerspaces and co-working spaces, and the restaurants that happily take large groups with little or no notice, I&#39;m very impressed!</p>
<p><strong>HSBXL</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/autonome/6800516745/" title="Performance work-week, Brussels 2012 by autonome, on Flickr"><img src="6800516745_02d5604af2.jpg" alt="Performance work-week, Brussels 2012"></a></p>
<p>The <a href="https://hackerspace.be/">hackerspace in Brussels</a> is located in Schaerbeek, a neighborhood to the north of the city center. The space used to be a vehicle repair garage for the city, but was given up for use by the geeks. They&#39;ve installed <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/autonome/6800517943/in/photostream" title="oscillosock!">serious hardware</a>, and have fully-equipped the place with <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/autonome/6800515533/in/photostream">everything needed for survival</a>. Thanks to Rafael and Patrick, for answering all our questions and helping us make <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mate_%28beverage%29">mate</a> and to find food nearby. Lunch on the second day was described by Patrick as a &quot;little French place&quot;, but turned out to be a hall of worship dedicated to Tintin!</p>
<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/autonome/6800526749/" title="Performance work-week, Brussels 2012 by autonome, on Flickr"><img src="6800526749_c9d485f250.jpg" alt="Performance work-week, Brussels 2012"></a></p>
<p>Faubourg St Antoine is filled with Tintin toys, art and <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/autonome/6800526217/in/photostream/">knick-knacks</a>, including some <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/autonome/6800525605/in/photostream/">alternate</a> interpretations and even a clarification for <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/autonome/6800523647/in/photostream">something I&#39;d always wondered about</a>. Sadly, they&#39;ve been issued a legal notice from the current copyright (or EU equivalent) holders requiring them to remove all the Tintin materials from public display :(</p>
<p><strong>BetaGroup Coworking</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/autonome/6800565749/" title="Performance work-week, Brussels 2012 by autonome, on Flickr"><img src="6800565749_99522d41d2.jpg" alt="Performance work-week, Brussels 2012"></a></p>
<p>Once the temperatures dropped far below freezing, we relocated to <a href="http://coworking.betagroup.be/">BetaGroup Coworking Brussels</a> in Etterbeek, to the southeast of the center. <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/ramonsuarez">Ramon Suarez</a>, the manager of the space was very accommodating, taking us on short notice. The wi-fi was blazing fast, the coffee was hot, and the ping-pong was a welcome break from heads-down hackery. The space itself was fantastic, with a great combination of quiet co-working areas, public spaces and private meeting offices. With tons of natural light, <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/autonome/6800566217/in/set-72157629096248615">steel bridges</a> and a meeting space on what looked like <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/autonome/6800567379/in/set-72157629096248615">a submarine conning tower</a>, it was truly impressive.</p>
<p>We had a wonderful lunch at a <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/autonome/6811646793/in/set-72157629096248615">very tidy restaurant</a> nearby.</p>
<p>Overall, it&#39;s been a fun and productive week, if a bit chilly. Like, really chilly. Ridiculously so. Why do people even inhabit places that get this cold? Honestly, wtf.</p>
]]></description><link>/2012/02/brussels-warm-hospitality-amidst-inhuman-conditions/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2012/02/brussels-warm-hospitality-amidst-inhuman-conditions/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[belgium]]></category><category><![CDATA[brussels]]></category><category><![CDATA[coworking]]></category><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[hackerspace]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2012 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>