<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[undefined - Dietrich Ayala]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internet freedom, the web and Mozilla.]]></description><link>/</link><generator>Ghost</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2018 11:41:26 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tag/undefined/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Jetpacking: The 0.3 SDK and a peek at what's coming next.]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I&#39;ve been working on the Jetpack project for about a month now - implementing features, fixing bugs, and generally helping move things forward as we build out the wide set of capabilities needed to enable an <em>awesome</em> future for Firefox add-on development.</p>
<p>The Jetpack team <a href="http://mozillalabs.com/jetpack/2010/04/29/announcing-jetpack-sdk-0-3/">released the 0.3 version of the SDK</a> yesterday, which has a bunch of platform improvements, and also the <a href="https://jetpack.mozillalabs.com/sdk/0.3/docs/#module/jetpack-core/context-menu">context menu API</a> - the first UI feature to ship in the SDK. The <a href="https://jetpack.mozillalabs.com/sdk/0.3/docs/#guide/programs">SDK documentation has an example</a> of using this feature that shows 1) how easy it is to build UI features with Jetpack, but also 2) shows how add-on development process has <em>changed</em> with the SDK. For example, all of the manual packaging steps are <em>gone</em>. That&#39;s right. No more crazy directory structures, no more RDF files, no more GUIDs. All of that stuff is gone, replaced with a couple of simple commands. It&#39;s not perfect yet, but expect it to get even easier to both package and deploy add-ons as we build out the SDK further.</p>
<p>So what&#39;s next? The 0.4 release is where the feature set of the SDK really starts to blow up:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Labs/Jetpack/Reboot/JEP/103">Panels</a>: Floating rich content, tooltips, contextual UI.</li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Labs/Jetpack/Reboot/JEP/116">Private Browsing</a>: Making it easy for add-ons to respect your privacy.</li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Labs/Jetpack/Reboot/JEP/111">Selection</a>: Remember how awesome it was having an intuitive selection API in Ubiquity?</li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Labs/Jetpack/Reboot/JEP/113">Localization</a>: Simple access and distribution of locale data.</li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Labs/Jetpack/Reboot/JEP/108">Page Worker</a>: Like a <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/En/Using_web_workers">Web Worker</a>, but with more privileges and a DOM.</li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Labs/Jetpack/Reboot/JEP/104">Simple Storage</a>: Persistent object store - like DOMStorage for add-ons.</li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Labs/Jetpack/Reboot/JEP/114">Places</a>: Improved bookmarks and history searching and browsing.</li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Labs/Jetpack/Reboot/JEP/102">Widgets</a>: A preview of the ideas <a href="http://mozillalabs.com/jetpack/2010/04/08/the-single-ui-element/">Daniel</a> and <a href="http://jboriss.wordpress.com/2010/04/29/removing-firefoxs-status-bar-and-rehousing-add-on-icons-part-1-of-2/">Boriss</a> have recently blogged about.</li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Labs/Jetpack/Reboot/JEP/109">Request</a>: Even easier AJAX (Please don&#39;t make that into an acronym. Please.)</li>
<li>Installable without needing to restart Firefox (trunk builds only).</li>
<li>Documentation: More and better!
And it&#39;s not just about the feature set: The diligent focus of the Jetpack core team on developer ergonomics, and the experience gained from the Jetpack prototype and projects like Ubiquity, is resulting in a set of APIs that are far more intuitive and easy to use than the current XPCOM-riddled minefield that add-on developers have to deal with today.</li>
</ul>
<p>If you have questions or suggestions, let me know in the comments, or join us on <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/mozilla-labs-jetpack">Jetpack developer forum</a>.</p>
]]></description><link>/2010/05/jetpacking-the-0-3-sdk-and-a-peek-at-whats-coming-next/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2010/05/jetpacking-the-0-3-sdk-and-a-peek-at-whats-coming-next/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[jetpack]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2010 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Easing Orange: Jetpack for Correlating Tinderbox Test Failures with Bugs]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This is a <a href="https://jetpack.mozillalabs.com/">Jetpack </a>feature for finding out if a bug is already filed for a test failure on <a href="http://tinderbox.mozilla.org/showbuilds.cgi?tree=Firefox">Tinderbox</a>. When viewing log files for failed test runs, the Jetpack will add a link next to the test failure summary at the top of the log, that looks like &quot;(maybe bug XXXXXX?)&quot;. This allows sheriff&#39;s and other awesome community members to easily mark known-oranges, and update the bug with log&#39;s URL.</p>
<p><a href="http://people.mozilla.org/~dietrich/jetpack-orange.html">Install the Jetpack feature</a>.</p>
<p>Notes:</p>
<ul>
<li>So far it only pulls file names out of error text, so won&#39;t match leaks, crashes or oranges without a filename in the summary.</li>
<li>Only searches the bug summary, and only searches known orange bugs (ie: has &quot;[orange]&quot; in the bug whiteboard).</li>
<li>Scrapes bugzilla.mozilla.org, since the new REST api is very very slow, so might break with bugzilla upgrades.</li>
<li>It doesn&#39;t run until the log has completed loading, which sometimes can  be a while. Load that shit in a background tab and be patient yo.
Let me know if this helps you out, or any bugs or improvements you&#39;d like to see!</li>
</ul>
]]></description><link>/2009/11/easing-orange-jetpack-for-correlating-tinderbox-test-failures-with-bugs/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2009/11/easing-orange-jetpack-for-correlating-tinderbox-test-failures-with-bugs/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[jetpack]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><category><![CDATA[tinderbox]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2009 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>