<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala - Dietrich Ayala]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internet freedom, the web and Mozilla.]]></description><link>/</link><generator>Ghost</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 15:51:57 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/author//rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Live Screencasting on a Mac with Mogulus and CamTwist]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This is bare-bones for now, just basic instructions to point folks at.</p>
<ol>
<li>Download and install <a href="http://www.macupdate.com/info.php/id/24275/camtwist">CamTwist</a></li>
<li>Go to <a href="http://www.mogulus.com">Mogulus.com</a> create an account and a new channel</li>
<li>Start CamTwist</li>
<li>Select &quot;Desktop&quot; from the video sources list on the far left</li>
<li>Select &quot;Full Screen&quot; from the settings pane on the far right</li>
<li>Restart your browser (yes, do it)</li>
<li>Log in to your channel&#39;s studio on Mogulus.com</li>
<li>On the left, in the Sources section, under the Cameras tab, your camera should show up</li>
<li>In your camera settings, select &quot;CamTwist&quot; as the Video Source, and click the Cue button</li>
<li>On the right, in the &quot;Cued clip&quot; section, press the big &quot;Transition to cued clip&quot; button
Boom, you&#39;re now screencasting live.</li>
</ol>
]]></description><link>/2008/06/live-screencasting-on-a-mac-with-mogulus-and-camtwist/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2008/06/live-screencasting-on-a-mac-with-mogulus-and-camtwist/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Mac]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mac]]></category><category><![CDATA[OSX]]></category><category><![CDATA[OSX]]></category><category><![CDATA[screencasting]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2008 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Installing the Lexmark P4350 on Mac OS X Leopard]]></title><description><![CDATA[<ol>
<li>Uninstall the printer, if already installed from a previous version of OS X, or from previous attempts to install Lexmark&#39;s drivers</li>
<li>Open Finder, click on your HD, find Library/Printers/Lexmark, and rename it to Lexmark.bak</li>
<li>Reboot</li>
<li>Insert your Leopard DVD, double-click Optional Installs, double-click Optional Installs.mpkg</li>
<li>When Optional Installs has loaded, open Printer Drivers, and check the box next to Lexmark, then finish the installation process.</li>
<li>Open System Preferences, and then Printer and Fax</li>
<li>Click the + sign to add a new printer</li>
<li>Your P4350 should show up as &quot;4300 Series Printer&quot; in the list. Select it.</li>
<li>The dialog may spin for a few minutes. When done, it will enable the driver selection list. Select &quot;4300 Series&quot; from the list and click OK.
You should now be able to print. I did this on two different Macs, and it worked for both.</li>
</ol>
]]></description><link>/2008/06/installing-the-lexmark-p4350-on-mac-os-x-leopard/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2008/06/installing-the-lexmark-p4350-on-mac-os-x-leopard/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Apple]]></category><category><![CDATA[Leopard]]></category><category><![CDATA[Lexmark]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mac]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mac]]></category><category><![CDATA[OS]]></category><category><![CDATA[X]]></category><category><![CDATA[OSX]]></category><category><![CDATA[P4350]]></category><category><![CDATA[printers]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2008 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Knowmore Extension debuts at NetSquared 2008!]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I spent some time last week helping out a group of folks to get a Firefox extension up and running for <a href="http://www.knowmore.org">Knowmore.org</a>. It was a great experience - a testament to the power of distributed volunteer software development as well as how Firefox as a platform can enable such groups to rapidly build and deploy world-changing tools. As <a href="http://www.knowmore.org/knowmore-blog/?p=86">officially announced on Knowmore.org</a> today, the extension is live! For screenshots and details, check out the <a href="http://www.knowmore.org/wiki/index.php?title=KnowMore_Firefox_Extension" title="KnowMore_Firefox_Extension">wiki page</a>, and you can <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/7342">install it here</a> (still sandboxed, login is required).</p>
<p>I was first tipped off by <a href="http://weblogs.mozillazine.org/asa/archives/2008/04/are_you_an_exte.html">Asa Dotzler&#39;s call</a> for extension developers to help out. I didn&#39;t follow up for weeks, as I was busy working on Firefox 3, trying to close up shop for release. Eventually, the smoke started to clear, and I poked <a href="http://www.engagejoe.com/">Joe Solomon</a>, social media extraordinaire, asking where the project was at. The timing was fortuitous: They were sprinting to get the extension ready for <a href="http://www.netsquared.org/">NetSquared 2008</a>. I hopped in, and found that a group of stellar developers already had the building blocks in place. The extension just needed some pieces glued together, and then once the API went live, it was mostly just polish from there on out.</p>
<p>The extension itself acts as a simple lens through which to experience the web, a lens that brings into focus the business and political practices of corporations that you purchase from. How it works is fantastically simple: When you go to a website, Firefox displays a <a href="http://www.knowmore.org/wiki/images/e/e1/Americanapparelnotificationbar.png">notification bar at the top of the page</a>, for corporations that have business practices that you might be concerned about, as well as a link to read more. The extension also displays <a href="http://www.knowmore.org/wiki/images/e/ef/Americanapparelsearchresults.png">visual notifications in search engine results</a>, marking links to corporations of concern.</p>
<p>This visibility gives us, as web consumers, the power to make informed decisions about where we spend our money, ensuring that we don&#39;t inadvertently fund corporations that behave in a way we find unacceptable.</p>
<p>This is just the beginning, as Knowmore.org <a href="http://www.knowmore.org/wiki/index.php?title=Image:Apilogo.jpg" title="Image:Apilogo.jpg">provides an API</a> for accessing the corporate statistics data. I&#39;d love to see mobile interfaces for the site, integration into web video and TV sites, and support for more search engines.</p>
<p>You can help: Knowmore is a wiki! Start <a href="http://www.knowmore.org/wiki/index.php?title=Behind_the_Logos" title="Behind_the_Logos">browsing existing corporate data</a>, and you see something missing or incorrect, or you know of another subsidiary, jump in and edit the page.</p>
<p>And if you&#39;re at NetSquared today, it looks like <a href="http://www.numenity.org/blog/2008/05/23/heading-to-netsquared-2008/">Paul Kim</a>, VP of marketing for Mozilla, and some folks from <a href="http://www.getmiro.com">Miro</a> will be there, so say hi!</p>
]]></description><link>/2008/05/knowmore-extension-debuts-at-netsquared-2008/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2008/05/knowmore-extension-debuts-at-netsquared-2008/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[activism]]></category><category><![CDATA[activism]]></category><category><![CDATA[api]]></category><category><![CDATA[ethical]]></category><category><![CDATA[consumerism]]></category><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[extensions]]></category><category><![CDATA[knowmore]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2008 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Firefox Support Day]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Today, I hosted a workshop on bookmarks, tagging and history for <a href="http://support.mozilla.com/en-US/kb/Support+Firefox+Day">Firefox Support Day</a>! If was pretty fun, and very different from the development grind of late. Some thoughts about the experience:</p>
<ul>
<li>I&#39;ve had my head in the Firefox 3 sand for a <em>long</em> time. Trying.. to remember.. how to.. talk..</li>
<li>SUMO is <em>fantastic</em>. I had no idea what it was until today... and I am ashamed for that.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.djst.org/blog/">David Tenser</a> is truly a gentleman.</li>
<li>Live screen-sharing with audio... worldwide... free... on the web, is a PAIN. We did not accomplish this, and resorted to a phone conference for audio.
It&#39;s nice to be out in society again. Who knows, maybe I&#39;ll even blog more.</li>
</ul>
]]></description><link>/2008/05/firefox-support-day/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2008/05/firefox-support-day/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2008 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Tweez 0.4: Migrating folders to tags]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Prompted by <a href="http://forums.mozillazine.org/viewtopic.php?t=649999&amp;start=0&amp;postdays=0&amp;postorder=asc&amp;highlight=">a request</a> in the build forum, I&#39;ve added a feature that allows you to tag all bookmarks with the name of their containing folder. It also provides the option to tag the bookmark with the name of each ancestor folder in the hierarchy. For example, given a folder hierarchy of Folder1/Folder2/Bookmark1, Bookmark1 would be tagged with both &quot;Folder1&quot; and &quot;Folder2&quot;.</p>
<p><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/6353">Install Tweez</a></p>
]]></description><link>/2008/04/tweez-04-migrating-folders-to-tags/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2008/04/tweez-04-migrating-folders-to-tags/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2008 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Tweez: now with tag auto[complete]]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to Adam Souzis, Tweez now has tag autocomplete. The other change is that ESC now cancels any changes and closes the panel.</p>
<p><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/6353">Get it</a>. Got it. Good.</p>
]]></description><link>/2008/02/tweez-now-with-tag-autocomplete/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2008/02/tweez-now-with-tag-autocomplete/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2008 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[tweez: extension for kui tagging in firefox 3]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Tweez is a simple keyboard-oriented extension to Firefox 3 that allows you to rapidly tag the page currently visible.</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/6353">Install</a></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Requires Firefox 3 Beta 2 or greater.</li>
<li>Shift+T to tag</li>
<li>Esc or Enter to leave</li>
</ul>
<p>Tweez is a hacky low-budget attempt to scratch an itch. Expect bugs, especially focus problems. Maybe someday it&#39;ll be cool like <a href="http://people.mozilla.com/~faaborg/files/20070705-kui/i1kuiTagging.png_large.png">Alex&#39;s vision</a>.</p>
]]></description><link>/2008/01/tweez-extension-for-kui-tagging-in-firefox-3/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2008/01/tweez-extension-for-kui-tagging-in-firefox-3/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2008 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cooking in Asia this week]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>The food. Cookbooks noted, and listed below.</p>
<ul>
<li>Sun: udon hot pot with chicken and shitaake (from Japanese Cooking...)</li>
<li>Mon: soba with prawns and tofu in chili sauce (from Wagamama)</li>
<li>Tues: udon with prawns, baby bok choy and tofu in tamarind sauce (from Wagamama)</li>
<li>Weds: tomato soup and veggie chicken nuggets (dinner fail: shiloh forgot to put a lid on the rice)</li>
<li>Thurs: Fukume-Ni (slow cooked shitaake, from Japanese Cooking...)</li>
<li>sushi rice - always keeping some in the fridge for meals, and Shiloh has been making onigiri for her school lunches</li>
<li>dashi - made a pint each of first and second dashi on sunday, using for various recipes, and miso soup at breakfast</li>
</ul>
<p>The Books:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0681323272/dietrganx4com-20">Japanese Cooking...</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1904920233/dietrganx4com-20">The Wagamama Cookbook</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1579651143/dietrganx4com-20">Hot Sour Salty Sweet</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0385339984/dietrganx4com-20">Japanese Women Don&#39;t Get Old or Fat</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0894807544/dietrganx4com-20">China Moon</a></li>
</ul>
]]></description><link>/2008/01/cooking-in-asia-this-week/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2008/01/cooking-in-asia-this-week/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Food]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2008 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Session Restore PSA]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to efforts of many people in the Mozilla community, combined with tools like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DTrace">DTrace</a>, we seem to be awash in performance data and awareness these days. And in the wonderment of this new visiblity, <a href="http://blog.mozilla.com/rob-sayre/">Rob Sayre</a> and <a href="http://blogs.sun.com/brendan/">Brendan Gregg</a> noticed that <a href="http://wiki.mozilla.org/Session_Restore">Session Restore</a> was responsible for a significant portion of <a href="http://wiki.mozilla.org/Performance:Tinderbox_Tests#Tp.2C_Tp2_and_the_Pageloader_extension:_Page_load_time">page-load</a> time! (/me takes an anxious bow, and dodges the tomatoes)</p>
<p>There are a couple of opportunities for improvement, chronicled <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=398807">here</a>. The first approach we&#39;re trying out is to save and restore less back-history for each tab. Easy to implement, but it wasn&#39;t the first choice since it decreased the utility of the feature... or so we thought, until <a href="http://blog.mozilla.com/metrics">Alex Polvi</a> <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=398807#c45">provided some data</a> indicating that users very rarely go back further than 6 steps.</p>
<p>The change that landed today will reduce saving of back-history to 10 pages, from a default of 50. You can set the browser.sessionstore.max_tab_back_history pref to -1 if you want all tab history restored.</p>
<p>Comment on the bug if you&#39;re one of the &lt;1% who go back beyond 10, and are truly disgruntled about this change. Or better yet, fix my patch to cache tab history :)</p>
]]></description><link>/2008/01/session-restore-psa/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2008/01/session-restore-psa/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2008 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mozilla Time Machine]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I hooked up <a href="http://bonsai.mozilla.org/cvsquery.cgi?treeid=default&amp;module=all&amp;branch=HEAD&amp;branchtype=match&amp;dir=&amp;file=&amp;filetype=match&amp;who=&amp;whotype=match&amp;sortby=Date&amp;hours=&amp;date=explicit&amp;mindate=1196474882&amp;maxdate=1197079682&amp;cvsroot=%2Fcvsroot&amp;xml=true">Bonsai&#39;s XML API</a> to <a href="http://simile.mit.edu/timeline/">Simile&#39;s Timeline</a>, for a nice interactive timeline of check-ins to the Mozilla trunk. It&#39;s still kinda rough, but you can view the <a href="http://nakedtickler.com/timeline/timeline.html">timeline here</a>.</p>
<p>TODO:</p>
<ul>
<li>It takes about 5 seconds to load up the data, probably should cache the generated event XML.</li>
<li>Hook up the tinderbox JSON feed, overlaying performance numbers.</li>
<li>Integrate the wormhole feed, to project what will be checked-in in the future.</li>
</ul>
]]></description><link>/2007/12/mozilla-time-machine/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/12/mozilla-time-machine/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Firefox 3 Conversation]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>9:12 argyle: fx3 please
9:13 argyle: fx2 just crashed on me for the 10th time this week
9:13 Dietrich: nightlies are always here: <a href="http://ftp.mozilla.org/pub/mozilla.org/firefox/nightly/latest-trunk/">http://ftp.mozilla.org/pub/mozilla.org/firefox/nightly/latest-trunk/</a>
9:13 argyle: ur lucky session restore is there
9:13 Dietrich: i seriously have hundreds of tabs open, no crashes
9:14 Dietrich: one-click bookmarking, tagging, better mem usage, no crashy
9:14 Dietrich: use it
9:14 Dietrich: love it
9:14 Dietrich: actually the killer feature is this:
9:14 Dietrich: url bar autocomplete searches title and url and tags now
9:15 Dietrich: and uses a &quot;frecency&quot; algorithm to bubble up stuff
9:15 argyle: nice
9:15 argyle: me like that
9:15 Dietrich: also shows bookmarked and tagged icons in the dropdown
9:15 Dietrich: i&#39;m serious: i can&#39;t use fx2
9:15 Dietrich: because of the url bar changes alone
9:16 Dietrich: it&#39;s sooo painful to live without
9:16 Dietrich: that and turning autofill on == dope
9:17 argyle: I shall play with your little fox
9:17 argyle: oh feature request... on camino when I download something it has a &quot;SHOW&quot; button that opens finder to that folder and selects that file
9:17 argyle: u make fix in ff to do
9:18 Dietrich: done
9:18 Dietrich: download manager is completely rewritten
9:19 Dietrich: open dm -&gt; click on the &quot;i&quot; icon next to the download -&gt; it shows the path -&gt; click on the path -&gt; bing, finder opens up to that file
9:19 Dietrich: next please
9:19 argyle: yeaaaaaa
9:19 argyle: u make me feel special
9:20 Dietrich: we did it just 4 u</p>
<p>It got all X-rated after that, I&#39;ll spare you.</p>
]]></description><link>/2007/11/firefox-3-conversation/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/11/firefox-3-conversation/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Feed organization and entropy]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I use Google Reader to read feeds. I have a &quot;daily&quot; folder for feeds that I really need to keep up on, and everything else is filed away into about 20 other content-specific folders.</p>
<p>However, I realized that I only read the &quot;daily&quot; folder, and never look in any of the other folders. Ever. And I&#39;m continually paring down the contents of the &quot;daily&quot; folder, as I don&#39;t have time to keep up with those either.</p>
<p>In fact, I&#39;d stopped reading about music, food, art, design, inventions, <a href="http://www.gadget-madness.net/">gadgets</a>, <a href="http://www.clubmogames.com">free mobile games</a>, travel.</p>
<p>In the end, I was basically reading <a href="http://planet.mozilla.org">Planet Mozilla</a> and the <a href="http://wiki.mozilla.org/Special:Recentchanges">Mozilla wiki&#39;s &quot;recent changes&quot;</a>. And while I love Moz, that&#39;s a far too singular lens through which to vicariously experience life.</p>
<p>So, I&#39;m going for the &quot;river of news&quot; strategy: I&#39;ve moved all feeds into the root folder, and will prune from there. I&#39;ve hidden the folder tree (which I wasn&#39;t using anyway), which leaves more real estate for content. I&#39;ve interspersed my work with my play feeds, which will hopefully bring some variety into my digital walkabouts.</p>
<p>I have a followup task: to step away from the computer altogether at some point.</p>
<p>Ack, almost forgot about the &quot;entropy&quot; part of this post! While pruning feeds, I noticed that a bunch hadn&#39;t had any posts in a while. I checked out a few, and found that the feed URL had changed, but the author hadn&#39;t set up redirects, or published any notice at all on the feed. Lame.</p>
]]></description><link>/2007/10/feed-organization-and-entropy/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/10/feed-organization-and-entropy/index.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Firefox 3 Talk at Portland Web Innovators]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.pdxwi.com/">Portland Web Innovators</a> is a monthly meeting of web designers and developers in Portland, Oregon. One of the founders, <a href="http://www.adamduvander.com/">Adam Duvander</a> (of <a href="http://www.bestplaces.net/">Best Places</a> and <a href="http://www.wifipdx.com/">WifiPDX</a>), invited me to come speak about <a href="http://wiki.mozilla.org/Firefox3">Firefox 3</a>. I was told that the turnout was 3x normal, which was cool. <a href="http://www.isitedesign.com/">iSite Design</a> provided the venue, and the pizza, thanks y&#39;all :)</p>
<p>My <a href="http://dietrich.ganx4.com/mozilla/Fx3-WebInnovators.pdf">hastily-made presentation</a> is basically an overview of the user-facing features planned for Fx3 (with Schrep&#39;s #&#39;s slide thrown in to end on). Here are some impressions and take-aways:</p>
<ul>
<li>The group is mostly designers and web developers from small (1 person) to medium (40 people) sized companies. There were some independent contractors, and a few other people from various software/web-related fields.</li>
<li>People seemed generally interested in the &quot;information management&quot; stuff: places, microformats, content handling.</li>
<li>Significant crowd reaction when i said we&#39;d fix the &quot;save password only <em>after</em> a successful logon&quot; bug :)</li>
<li>Unsurprisingly, there was concern about how many new features there were. Several people asked whether the new features would be able to turned off entirely. Questions about whether &quot;the old simpler Firefox&quot; would still be available.</li>
<li>Also unsurprising was the general concern about performance and memory usage.</li>
<li>People were curious about developing both Firefox extensions and XULRunner apps.</li>
</ul>
<p>I might do a follow-up presentation on Fx3 for Developers.
<a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1014"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1016"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1017"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1018"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=102"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1023"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1029"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=103"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1031"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1034"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1035"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1036"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1037"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1038"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1039"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=104"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1043"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1045"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1046"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1047"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1048"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1049"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=105"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1050"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1053"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1054"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1055"> </a></p>
]]></description><link>/2007/04/firefox-3-talk-at-portland-web-innovators/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/04/firefox-3-talk-at-portland-web-innovators/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Bugzilla Patch Interdiff Greasemonkey Script]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This <a href="http://www.greasespot.net/">Greasemonkey</a> script adds a link to interdiff a bug&#39;s patch against the patch that precedes it, to attachments on a bug&#39;s detail page.</p>
<h2 id="-install-mozilla-bz-interdiff-user-js-"><a href="/mozilla/bz-interdiff.user.js">Install</a></h2>
<p>Based on <a href="http://beaufour.dk/">Allan Beaufour</a>&#39;s <a href="http://beaufour.dk/jst-review/">JST Review Greasemonkey script</a> (thanks!).</p>
]]></description><link>/2007/03/bugzilla-patch-interdiff-greasemonkey-script/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/03/bugzilla-patch-interdiff-greasemonkey-script/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[greasemonkey]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Chirp! Twitter Notifications in Firefox]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Chirp is a Firefox extension that pops up a notification when you have new Twitter messages.</p>
<p>Twitter via IM already provides instant gratification, so this is only really useful if you don&#39;t or can&#39;t use IM. For example, say you turn of IM to reduce distraction and increase your productivity. With Chirp, you&#39;ll still be in touch with what your friends are doing! Oh, wait...</p>
<h2 id="-install-http-dietrich-ganx4-com-foxylicious-chirp-xpi-"><a href="http://dietrich.ganx4.com/foxylicious/chirp.xpi">Install</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Configure your Twitter username and password in the preferences (tools/add-ons/chirp)</li>
<li>If you&#39;re on a Mac, you&#39;ll need to install <a href="http://growl.info/">Growl</a>.</li>
<li>It only checks Twitter every 30 minutes. Yeah, this kinda reduces the immediacy of Twitter, but you can tweak it via a pref: extensions.chirp.updateFrequency ;)</li>
</ul>
<p>Props to the <a href="http://www.songbirdnest.com/growl">Songbird Growl extension</a> for the Growl code. And yeah, the icon looks like ass (but not in a good way), so please send me a better one!</p>
<p>PS: I&#39;m a <a href="http://twitter.com/dietrich">twit</a>.</p>
]]></description><link>/2007/03/chirp-twitter-notifications-in-firefox/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/03/chirp-twitter-notifications-in-firefox/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>