<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[undefined - Dietrich Ayala]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internet freedom, the web and Mozilla.]]></description><link>/</link><generator>Ghost</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2017 11:00:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tag/undefined/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[FOSSAsia 2017]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Seven years after attending my first FOSSAsia in Ho Chi Min City, I was able to join again this year! The difference is amazing - the conference has grown to be one of the largest open source events in Asia, with more than <a href="http://2017.fossasia.org/speakers.html">200 speakers</a> over three days across 13 tracks and now hosted in Singapore.</p>
<script src="//unpkg.com/twitter-inline-oembed@0.0.1/oembed.js?tweet=https://twitter.com/dietrich/status/842543000320335873"></script>

<p>The conference is entirely open source and volunteer-run, which is really neat. Kudos to the organizers for putting it on, which is a huge amount of work. The focus on free and open source software and tracks on relevant topics like AI, Bitcoin, and IoT combine to make a great collection of people to put in one place for a weekend.</p>
<script src="//unpkg.com/twitter-inline-oembed@0.0.1/oembed.js?tweet=https://twitter.com/dietrich/status/842638503473233921"></script>

<p>Mozilla didn&#39;t directly sponsor this year, but instead sent some of our Tech Speakers who had talks accepted and myself. We were seven people from six countries, speaking about VR, WebAssembly, Web-RTC, security, IoT, AR and more. Big thanks to Bob Reyes, Diky Arga Anggara, Noritada Shimizu, Santosh Viswanatham, Shah Mijanur Rahman and Trishul Goel for speaking at the conference and putting in a bunch of hours at our table every day.</p>
<script src="//unpkg.com/twitter-inline-oembed@0.0.1/oembed.js?tweet=https://twitter.com/dietrich/status/843647232393924609"></script>

<p>The number of speakers was enough of a presence to earn us a table in the exhibition hall, so we took advantage of the opportunity and demo&#39;d A-Frame VR and AR on mobile devices for all three days.</p>
<p>The response was <em>fantastic</em> - lots of people having their first VR experience of any kind, and everyone was mindblown that the demos were built using web technologies, running in a browser, and on a mobile phone.</p>
<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/comprock/32663678044/in/faves-49503183968@N01/" title="FOSSASIA 2017"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/4/3788/32663678044_8a8e2d7b12_z.jpg" width="640" height="427" alt="FOSSASIA 2017"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
<p>After three days of rapping with everyone who came by the booth, here are a few impressions:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Most people, developers included, haven&#39;t strongly engaged in VR yet. If you assume everyone is doing it, you&#39;re probably in the VR industry and you&#39;re wrong. I&#39;ve been demoing VR at conferences for the last couple of years and I always ask if people have tried it before and the answer is usually &quot;no&quot;. VR may be in the limelight in tech news, but the on-the-ground experience says it&#39;s still very early days.</p>
</li>
<li><p>A-Frame has excellent name recognition. This conversation a lot: &quot;This was made with a JavaScript library called A-Frame.&quot; &quot;Oh, A-Frame!&quot; &quot;You&#39;ve used it?&quot; &quot;No, but I&#39;ve heard of it and it looks awesome!&quot;.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Almost nobody was talking about bots.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Almost everybody was talking about AI and machine learning.</p>
</li>
<li><p>People are <em>still</em> asking us about Firefox OS.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conference">Conference</h2>
<p>What I liked:</p>
<ul>
<li>Great crowd. It really feels like a practitioners conference where people are learning reciprocally.</li>
<li>Talk topics are really good. Very little fluff on the schedule. Great mix of interesting and practical topics. Good job by organizers here.</li>
<li>Excellent conference website and apps. They&#39;re writing their own FOSS event management stack, and it seems pretty great so far.</li>
<li>Communication from organizers prior to the event was really good. Combination of emails for important things, and Google Group and Slack for general communication really worked well.</li>
</ul>
<p>What I&#39;d like to see next year:</p>
<ul>
<li>Speakers should not have to pay for tickets.</li>
<li>Need a venue that&#39;s centrally located, easier to navigate and that lets attendees focus on the conference.</li>
<li>Singapore already has lots of events, and is famously expensive for hotel and venue space. To make a truly pan-Asian conference, should move around to different cities.</li>
<li>The schedule was changed at the last minute without warning to speakers, causing some to miss their talks. Need to lock the schedule down, and communicate changes very clearly.</li>
<li>Day two and three each have <em>15</em> tracks! I&#39;d prefer to see a smaller and more focused set of tracks.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="social-photos-whatnot">Social, Photos, Whatnot</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/comprock/32663731524/in/pool-fossasia-2017-singapore/">FOSSAsia pool on Flickr</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/comprock/albums/72157678094595694">FOSSAsia official photog&#39;s photos</a></li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/search?f=tweets&amp;vertical=default&amp;q=%23FOSSASIA&amp;src=tyah">#fossasia on Twitter</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/fossasia/">#fossasia on Instagram</a></li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/search?f=tweets&amp;vertical=default&amp;q=%23fossasia%20from%3Adietrich&amp;src=typd">My FOSSAsia 2017 tweets</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="our-talks">Our Talks</h2>
<p>Huge thanks to <a href="https://engineers.sg">Engineers.sg</a>, who recorded almost all of talks. The complete set of FOSSAsia 2017 recorded talks is <a href="https://engineers.sg/conference/fossasia-2017">here on their website</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://engineers.sg/video/opensec-and-why-webappsec-matters-fossasia-2017--1547">OpenSec and Why WebAppSec Matters - Shah Mijanur Rahman (SYLHET, Bangladesh)</a></p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8KK-lQQfYXs?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://engineers.sg/video/tea-linux-os-designed-for-programmer-developer-fossasia-2017--1591">Tea Linux OS, Designed for Programmer / Developer - Diky Arga Anggara (Semarang, Indonesia)</a></p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tRa5lLWWY94?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://engineers.sg/video/creating-your-own-pokemon-world-in-web-based-virtual-reality-workshop-1hr-fossasia-2017--1553">Creating your own Pokemon-world in Web based Virtual Reality - Santosh Viswanatham (Hyderabad, India)</a></p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/e4HbnJ_-u0o?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://engineers.sg/video/webrtc-future-of-video-chats-fossasia-2017--1548">WebRTC - future of Video Chats - Trishul Goel (Delhi, India)</a></p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7hEVzSUv7sg?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://engineers.sg/video/webassembly-now-web-is-a-new-compiler-target-architecture-fossasia-2017--1555">WebAssembly: now web is a new compiler target architecture - Noritada Shimizu (Tokyo, Japan)</a></p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VAcyLP9RdfQ?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://engineers.sg/video/integrated-physical-computing-on-the-web-fossasia-2017--1567">Integrated Physical Computing on the Web - Dietrich Ayala (Portland, OR, USA)</a></p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_TWGDklUlD4?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thanks-fossasia-">THANKS FOSSASIA!</h2>
<p><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/4/3729/33465175206_fe8587590e_z.jpg" alt="FOSSAsia 2017 Group Photo"></p>
]]></description><link>/2017/03/28/fossasia2017/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2017/03/28/fossasia2017/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Events]]></category><category><![CDATA[Asia]]></category><category><![CDATA[2017]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>