<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala - Dietrich Ayala]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internet freedom, the web and Mozilla.]]></description><link>/</link><generator>Ghost</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Nov 2018 12:52:25 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/author//rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Session Restore PSA]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to efforts of many people in the Mozilla community, combined with tools like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DTrace">DTrace</a>, we seem to be awash in performance data and awareness these days. And in the wonderment of this new visiblity, <a href="http://blog.mozilla.com/rob-sayre/">Rob Sayre</a> and <a href="http://blogs.sun.com/brendan/">Brendan Gregg</a> noticed that <a href="http://wiki.mozilla.org/Session_Restore">Session Restore</a> was responsible for a significant portion of <a href="http://wiki.mozilla.org/Performance:Tinderbox_Tests#Tp.2C_Tp2_and_the_Pageloader_extension:_Page_load_time">page-load</a> time! (/me takes an anxious bow, and dodges the tomatoes)</p>
<p>There are a couple of opportunities for improvement, chronicled <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=398807">here</a>. The first approach we&#39;re trying out is to save and restore less back-history for each tab. Easy to implement, but it wasn&#39;t the first choice since it decreased the utility of the feature... or so we thought, until <a href="http://blog.mozilla.com/metrics">Alex Polvi</a> <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=398807#c45">provided some data</a> indicating that users very rarely go back further than 6 steps.</p>
<p>The change that landed today will reduce saving of back-history to 10 pages, from a default of 50. You can set the browser.sessionstore.max_tab_back_history pref to -1 if you want all tab history restored.</p>
<p>Comment on the bug if you&#39;re one of the &lt;1% who go back beyond 10, and are truly disgruntled about this change. Or better yet, fix my patch to cache tab history :)</p>
]]></description><link>/2008/01/session-restore-psa/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2008/01/session-restore-psa/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2008 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mozilla Time Machine]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I hooked up <a href="http://bonsai.mozilla.org/cvsquery.cgi?treeid=default&amp;module=all&amp;branch=HEAD&amp;branchtype=match&amp;dir=&amp;file=&amp;filetype=match&amp;who=&amp;whotype=match&amp;sortby=Date&amp;hours=&amp;date=explicit&amp;mindate=1196474882&amp;maxdate=1197079682&amp;cvsroot=%2Fcvsroot&amp;xml=true">Bonsai&#39;s XML API</a> to <a href="http://simile.mit.edu/timeline/">Simile&#39;s Timeline</a>, for a nice interactive timeline of check-ins to the Mozilla trunk. It&#39;s still kinda rough, but you can view the <a href="http://nakedtickler.com/timeline/timeline.html">timeline here</a>.</p>
<p>TODO:</p>
<ul>
<li>It takes about 5 seconds to load up the data, probably should cache the generated event XML.</li>
<li>Hook up the tinderbox JSON feed, overlaying performance numbers.</li>
<li>Integrate the wormhole feed, to project what will be checked-in in the future.</li>
</ul>
]]></description><link>/2007/12/mozilla-time-machine/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/12/mozilla-time-machine/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Firefox 3 Conversation]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>9:12 argyle: fx3 please
9:13 argyle: fx2 just crashed on me for the 10th time this week
9:13 Dietrich: nightlies are always here: <a href="http://ftp.mozilla.org/pub/mozilla.org/firefox/nightly/latest-trunk/">http://ftp.mozilla.org/pub/mozilla.org/firefox/nightly/latest-trunk/</a>
9:13 argyle: ur lucky session restore is there
9:13 Dietrich: i seriously have hundreds of tabs open, no crashes
9:14 Dietrich: one-click bookmarking, tagging, better mem usage, no crashy
9:14 Dietrich: use it
9:14 Dietrich: love it
9:14 Dietrich: actually the killer feature is this:
9:14 Dietrich: url bar autocomplete searches title and url and tags now
9:15 Dietrich: and uses a &quot;frecency&quot; algorithm to bubble up stuff
9:15 argyle: nice
9:15 argyle: me like that
9:15 Dietrich: also shows bookmarked and tagged icons in the dropdown
9:15 Dietrich: i&#39;m serious: i can&#39;t use fx2
9:15 Dietrich: because of the url bar changes alone
9:16 Dietrich: it&#39;s sooo painful to live without
9:16 Dietrich: that and turning autofill on == dope
9:17 argyle: I shall play with your little fox
9:17 argyle: oh feature request... on camino when I download something it has a &quot;SHOW&quot; button that opens finder to that folder and selects that file
9:17 argyle: u make fix in ff to do
9:18 Dietrich: done
9:18 Dietrich: download manager is completely rewritten
9:19 Dietrich: open dm -&gt; click on the &quot;i&quot; icon next to the download -&gt; it shows the path -&gt; click on the path -&gt; bing, finder opens up to that file
9:19 Dietrich: next please
9:19 argyle: yeaaaaaa
9:19 argyle: u make me feel special
9:20 Dietrich: we did it just 4 u</p>
<p>It got all X-rated after that, I&#39;ll spare you.</p>
]]></description><link>/2007/11/firefox-3-conversation/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/11/firefox-3-conversation/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Feed organization and entropy]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I use Google Reader to read feeds. I have a &quot;daily&quot; folder for feeds that I really need to keep up on, and everything else is filed away into about 20 other content-specific folders.</p>
<p>However, I realized that I only read the &quot;daily&quot; folder, and never look in any of the other folders. Ever. And I&#39;m continually paring down the contents of the &quot;daily&quot; folder, as I don&#39;t have time to keep up with those either.</p>
<p>In fact, I&#39;d stopped reading about music, food, art, design, inventions, <a href="http://www.gadget-madness.net/">gadgets</a>, <a href="http://www.clubmogames.com">free mobile games</a>, travel.</p>
<p>In the end, I was basically reading <a href="http://planet.mozilla.org">Planet Mozilla</a> and the <a href="http://wiki.mozilla.org/Special:Recentchanges">Mozilla wiki&#39;s &quot;recent changes&quot;</a>. And while I love Moz, that&#39;s a far too singular lens through which to vicariously experience life.</p>
<p>So, I&#39;m going for the &quot;river of news&quot; strategy: I&#39;ve moved all feeds into the root folder, and will prune from there. I&#39;ve hidden the folder tree (which I wasn&#39;t using anyway), which leaves more real estate for content. I&#39;ve interspersed my work with my play feeds, which will hopefully bring some variety into my digital walkabouts.</p>
<p>I have a followup task: to step away from the computer altogether at some point.</p>
<p>Ack, almost forgot about the &quot;entropy&quot; part of this post! While pruning feeds, I noticed that a bunch hadn&#39;t had any posts in a while. I checked out a few, and found that the feed URL had changed, but the author hadn&#39;t set up redirects, or published any notice at all on the feed. Lame.</p>
]]></description><link>/2007/10/feed-organization-and-entropy/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/10/feed-organization-and-entropy/index.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Firefox 3 Talk at Portland Web Innovators]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.pdxwi.com/">Portland Web Innovators</a> is a monthly meeting of web designers and developers in Portland, Oregon. One of the founders, <a href="http://www.adamduvander.com/">Adam Duvander</a> (of <a href="http://www.bestplaces.net/">Best Places</a> and <a href="http://www.wifipdx.com/">WifiPDX</a>), invited me to come speak about <a href="http://wiki.mozilla.org/Firefox3">Firefox 3</a>. I was told that the turnout was 3x normal, which was cool. <a href="http://www.isitedesign.com/">iSite Design</a> provided the venue, and the pizza, thanks y&#39;all :)</p>
<p>My <a href="http://dietrich.ganx4.com/mozilla/Fx3-WebInnovators.pdf">hastily-made presentation</a> is basically an overview of the user-facing features planned for Fx3 (with Schrep&#39;s #&#39;s slide thrown in to end on). Here are some impressions and take-aways:</p>
<ul>
<li>The group is mostly designers and web developers from small (1 person) to medium (40 people) sized companies. There were some independent contractors, and a few other people from various software/web-related fields.</li>
<li>People seemed generally interested in the &quot;information management&quot; stuff: places, microformats, content handling.</li>
<li>Significant crowd reaction when i said we&#39;d fix the &quot;save password only <em>after</em> a successful logon&quot; bug :)</li>
<li>Unsurprisingly, there was concern about how many new features there were. Several people asked whether the new features would be able to turned off entirely. Questions about whether &quot;the old simpler Firefox&quot; would still be available.</li>
<li>Also unsurprising was the general concern about performance and memory usage.</li>
<li>People were curious about developing both Firefox extensions and XULRunner apps.</li>
</ul>
<p>I might do a follow-up presentation on Fx3 for Developers.
<a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1014"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1016"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1017"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1018"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=102"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1023"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1029"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=103"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1031"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1034"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1035"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1036"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1037"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1038"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1039"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=104"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1043"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1045"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1046"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1047"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1048"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1049"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=105"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1050"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1053"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1054"> </a><a href="http://www.videosz.com/movie.php?link_id=5927&amp;lg=us&amp;dvd_id=1055"> </a></p>
]]></description><link>/2007/04/firefox-3-talk-at-portland-web-innovators/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/04/firefox-3-talk-at-portland-web-innovators/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Bugzilla Patch Interdiff Greasemonkey Script]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This <a href="http://www.greasespot.net/">Greasemonkey</a> script adds a link to interdiff a bug&#39;s patch against the patch that precedes it, to attachments on a bug&#39;s detail page.</p>
<h2 id="-install-mozilla-bz-interdiff-user-js-"><a href="/mozilla/bz-interdiff.user.js">Install</a></h2>
<p>Based on <a href="http://beaufour.dk/">Allan Beaufour</a>&#39;s <a href="http://beaufour.dk/jst-review/">JST Review Greasemonkey script</a> (thanks!).</p>
]]></description><link>/2007/03/bugzilla-patch-interdiff-greasemonkey-script/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/03/bugzilla-patch-interdiff-greasemonkey-script/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[greasemonkey]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Chirp! Twitter Notifications in Firefox]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Chirp is a Firefox extension that pops up a notification when you have new Twitter messages.</p>
<p>Twitter via IM already provides instant gratification, so this is only really useful if you don&#39;t or can&#39;t use IM. For example, say you turn of IM to reduce distraction and increase your productivity. With Chirp, you&#39;ll still be in touch with what your friends are doing! Oh, wait...</p>
<h2 id="-install-http-dietrich-ganx4-com-foxylicious-chirp-xpi-"><a href="http://dietrich.ganx4.com/foxylicious/chirp.xpi">Install</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Configure your Twitter username and password in the preferences (tools/add-ons/chirp)</li>
<li>If you&#39;re on a Mac, you&#39;ll need to install <a href="http://growl.info/">Growl</a>.</li>
<li>It only checks Twitter every 30 minutes. Yeah, this kinda reduces the immediacy of Twitter, but you can tweak it via a pref: extensions.chirp.updateFrequency ;)</li>
</ul>
<p>Props to the <a href="http://www.songbirdnest.com/growl">Songbird Growl extension</a> for the Growl code. And yeah, the icon looks like ass (but not in a good way), so please send me a better one!</p>
<p>PS: I&#39;m a <a href="http://twitter.com/dietrich">twit</a>.</p>
]]></description><link>/2007/03/chirp-twitter-notifications-in-firefox/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/03/chirp-twitter-notifications-in-firefox/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Thermals @ Crystal Ballroom]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>We went to see <a href="http://www.subpop.com/artists/the_thermals">The Thermals</a> last night. First time at the <a href="http://www.mcmenamins.com/index.php?loc=2&amp;category=Location%20Homepage">Crystal Ballroom</a>, in downtown Portland. It&#39;s a <a href="http://www.mcmenamins.com/">McMenamins</a> joint, and as to be expected it was a beautiful old space, renovated and covered with faux-hippie murals. The floor of the place is springy, kinda like gymnastics flooring, brilliant idea.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.teaforjulie.net/">
Tea for Julie</a> was on we got there. Hey guys, get a new band name.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.starsoftrackandfield.com/">Stars of Track and Field</a> were next. Wow I had no idea that you could have so many crescendos in a single song! Hey guys, it kinda detracts from the suspense WHEN THERE IS NONE. I believe this kind of music is known as &quot;anthemo&quot; (a-nth-ee-mo). They were interestingly derivative: The guitar had shades of 70s rock, U2, The Church. The vocals had a bit of Galaxy 500, and someone else that I haven&#39;t quite pinpointed yet. Sometimes they&#39;d bust out the cheesy drum machine and keyboard for some serious Postal Service rip-off action. Ok, I know it sounds like I hated them, but I actually really enjoyed some of the songs (especially those without the keyboard). Definitely talented guys... just haven&#39;t figured out who they want to sound like yet.</p>
<p>After an awesomely short wait (no pretension here!) The Thermals came on. Great show, as to be expected. However, the sound was not so hot, bad acoustics seemed to eat up the guitar punch. We saw them at the Wonder Ballroom (Portland&#39;s got lots of ballrooms it seems) last fall, and the sound there was much better.</p>
<p>The best part of the show though, was watching my daughter totally lose it when the Thermals played; she was head-banging throughout their set. Afterwards she was disappointed that &quot;it was so boring where we were&quot;. We were about 10 feet from the stage, the mosh pit was a few feet to the right, and some guy next to us was carried off basically unconscious from a blow to the head (due to a falling crowd-surfer). An explanation of basic mosh pit arithmetic ensued: falling 250 pound punker + 70 pound 11 year-old = emergency-room trip.</p>
<p>Maybe when you grow another few inches :)</p>
]]></description><link>/2007/02/thermals-crystal-ballroom/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2007/02/thermals-crystal-ballroom/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[music]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2007 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Happy Moz-o-ween!]]></title><description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p><img src="283823957_20e4af594d.jpg" alt="moz-o-lantern @ daytime"></p>
<p><img src="283820619_5801e02beb.jpg" alt="moz-o-lantern @ nighttime"></p>
</blockquote>
]]></description><link>/2006/10/happy-moz-o-ween/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2006/10/happy-moz-o-ween/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[halloween]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2006 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Foxylicious 0.7]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I updated <a href="http://dietrich.ganx4.com/foxylicious">Foxylicious</a> for <a href="http://www.mozilla.com/firefox/">Firefox 2</a>. It&#39;s home at <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/firefox/342/">AMO</a> is not yet updated, as it&#39;s still awaiting approval. For those who can&#39;t wait, I&#39;ve made it available here.</p>
<ul>
<li>Updated to work with Firefox 2</li>
<li>Uses the new secure del.icio.us API endpoint (fixes the auth prompt issue)</li>
<li>Fixed some pref handling errors</li>
<li>Added configurable post URLs. To load a different posting page, set the foxylicious.postURL to a URL that has %user%, %location% and %title%, for example, the default is: <a href="http://del.icio.us/%user%?v=2&amp;noui=yes&amp;jump=close&amp;url=%location%&amp;title=%title">http://del.icio.us/%user%?v=2&amp;noui=yes&amp;jump=close&amp;url=%location%&amp;title=%title</a></li>
<li>Properly localize-able</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://dietrich.ganx4.com/foxylicious/foxylicious.xpi">INSTALL Foxylicious 0.7</a></p>
<p>Please let me know if you have any problems, regressions, etc.</p>
<p>XOXO,</p>
<p>-d</p>
]]></description><link>/2006/10/foxylicious-07/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2006/10/foxylicious-07/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[foxylicious]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2006 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Firefox 2 and the Northwest Pressure-washing Gutter-cleaners]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Here in the Northwest the rainy season is upon us. So, the other day I searched <a href="http://portland.craigslist.org/">Craigslist</a> and hired someone to clean out the gutters and pressure-wash the roof of our house. They showed up today, and while chatting with them I mentioned that I work on Firefox. Not only had both of these guys heard of Firefox, but they got excited and said that it&#39;s their default browser.</p>
<p>Of course, I immediately used the opportunity to do that which is the point of this blog post: Plug Firefox 2.0 :)</p>
<ul>
<li>New theme</li>
<li>Anti-phishing</li>
<li>Microsummaries</li>
<li>Spell-check</li>
<li>Session-restore</li>
<li>Undo-close-tab</li>
<li>Search suggestions</li>
<li>Feed handling</li>
<li>And 23 other enhancements and bug-fixes (give or take a few thousand)</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://www.mozilla.com/firefox/">Download Firefox 2.0</a></p>
<p>Enjoy :)</p>
]]></description><link>/2006/10/firefox-2-and-the-northwest-pressure-washing-gutter-cleaners/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2006/10/firefox-2-and-the-northwest-pressure-washing-gutter-cleaners/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2006 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[You are under surveillance.]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Last night we went to a panel discussion on the Bush administration&#39;s warrant-less wiretapping program, at <a href="http://www.pdx.edu/">PSU</a> in downtown Portland. It was put on by the <a href="http://www.nwcrc.org/">NWCRC</a> and <a href="http://www.pfaw.org/pfaw/general/">PFAW</a>, and featured a professor/lawyer, a lawyer handling a case against the government over warrant-less wiretapping, and an activist.</p>
<p>It was f*ckin&#39; scary.</p>
<p>But it was also extremely interesting, and at times even funny. It&#39;s inspiring and humbling to see these smart and talented people out there fighting our government&#39;s encroachments on our rights, on a daily basis. And it&#39;s uplifting to see that it&#39;s possible to keep a sense of humor while doing it... because if we can no longer laugh, then the fascists have truly won.</p>
<p>Yes, you are under surveillance.</p>
<p><strong>DANCE!</strong></p>
]]></description><link>/2006/10/you-are-under-surveillance/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2006/10/you-are-under-surveillance/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[assholes]]></category><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[political]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2006 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Wife on the Telly, Kicking Ass and Taking Names]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>My wife <a href="http://www.girlwrites.com">Shauna</a> just started a fellowship at the <a href="http://www.nwcrc.org/">Northwest Constitutional Rights Center</a> as an attorney. During her first week on the job, there was an <a href="http://portland.indymedia.org/en/2006/10/347085.shtml">anti-Bush protest in downtown Portland</a>, that unfortunately turned violent when a group of protesters went off-route and were turned back by police, using pepper spray, rubber bullets and horses. Shauna was on one of the local news channels that night, giving the NWCRC&#39;s comment on what happened:</p>
<p><a href="http://dietrich.ganx4.com/movies/portland-protest-k2-coverage-10-5-06.mp4">Watch video</a> (6mb MPEG4)</p>
]]></description><link>/2006/10/wife-on-the-telly-kicking-ass-and-taking-names/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2006/10/wife-on-the-telly-kicking-ass-and-taking-names/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[political]]></category><category><![CDATA[politics]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><category><![CDATA[Videos]]></category><category><![CDATA[war]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2006 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cool it, baby.]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This software cocktail cooled my MacBook Pro by more than 40 degrees Fahrenheit:</p>
<ol>
<li>Install the <a href="http://shockwidgets.com/ministat2update1.8.htm">MiniStat2 Dashboard widget</a>. It shows CPU temperature as well as fan speed. This allows you to do easy before/after verification.</li>
<li>Install <a href="http://www.bernhard-baehr.de/">SleepWatcher,</a> which executes commands at wake/sleep events.</li>
<li>Finally, install <a href="http://members.optusnet.com.au/a1291762/2006/10/changing-fan-speed-to-beat-heat.html">FanSpeed</a>, which increases the minimum fan speed.</li>
</ol>
<p>Before: 132F
After: 84F</p>
<p>There are downsides (noticeable fan sound, uses more power), but having a laptop that I can have in my lap is well worth it.</p>
]]></description><link>/2006/10/entering-a-brave-new-world-of-lap-computing/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2006/10/entering-a-brave-new-world-of-lap-computing/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Apple]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2006 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mini-review: The Albina Press, North Portland (another coffeehouse)]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Great atmosphere, lots of places to sit inside and out. Sweet treats and Beta Band beats. Located a bit north of the main Mississippi area. It&#39;s east of Interstate 5, but the area seems to be referred to as North Portland, not Northeast.</p>
<ul>
<li>Wi-fi: free</li>
<li>Coffee: Stumptown</li>
<li>Food: cookies, scones, bagels</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;hl=en&amp;q=4637+N.+Albina+Ave,+portland+OR&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;om=1">Map</a></p>
]]></description><link>/2006/08/mini-review-the-albina-press-north-portland-another-coffeehouse/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2006/08/mini-review-the-albina-press-north-portland-another-coffeehouse/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[coffee]]></category><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[portland]]></category><category><![CDATA[reviews]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2006 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>