<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[undefined - Dietrich Ayala]]></title><description><![CDATA[Working towards true user agency through a distributed web.]]></description><link>/</link><generator>Ghost</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 02:32:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tag/undefined/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA["Open Letter to the World"]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><em>We  stand at a unique time in our history, the rise of the internet and  computer technology have contributed to an unparalleled rate of  prosperity for the First World.</em></p>
<p><em>We  have created for ourselves and empire unlike any other, a global  network of constant trade and communication, a new age of technological  advancement. We have come a long way from our humble roots in the  Industrial Revolution and the days of Manifest Destiny. We are now  pioneers on new digital frontiers expanding our domain from the quantum  world to the far reaches of space.</em></p>
<p><em>And  yet, the empire faces a crisis, a global recession, growing poverty,  rampant violence, corruption in politics, and threats to personal  freedom. As it was before in other times of crisis, the old stories have  begun to repeat themselves. The half truths, this time repeated nightly  on cable news and echoed through a series of tubes onto the internet:  the empire is strong, change is unwise, business as usual is the answer.  In times of uncertainty there are those who seek to add to the  confusion, to prey on our insecurities and fears. Those who would seek  to keep us divided for their own gain. The pervasive strategy takes many  very convincing forms: Liberals and Conservatives, Christians and  Muslims, Black and White, Saved and sinner.</em></p>
<p><em>But  something unexpected is happening. We have begun telling each other our  own stories. Sharing our lives, our hopes, our dreams, our demons.  Every second, day in day out, into all hours of the night the gritty  details of life on this earth are streaming around the world. As we see  the lives of others played out in our living rooms we are beginning to  understand the consequences of our actions and the error of the old  ways. We are questioning the old assumptions that we are made to consume  not to create, that the world was made for our taking, that wars are  inevitable, that poverty is unavoidable. As we learn more about our  global community a fundamental truth has been rediscovered: We are not  so different as we may seem. Every human has strengths, weaknesses, and  deep emotions. We crave love, love laughter, fear being alone and dream  for a better life.</em></p>
<p><em>You must create a better life.</em></p>
<p><em>You  cannot sit on the couch watching television or playing video games,  waiting for a revolution. You are the revolution. Every time you decide  not to exercise your rights, every time you refuse to hear another view  point, every time you ignore the world around you, every time you spend a  dollar at a business that doesn&#39;t pay a fair wage you are contributing  to the oppression of the human body and the repression of the human  mind. You have a choice, a choice to take the easy path, the familiar  path, to walk willingly into your own submission. Or a choice get up, to  go outside and talk to your neighbor, to come together in new forums to  create lasting, meaningful change for the human race.</em></p>
<p><em>This is our challenge:</em></p>
<p><em>A  peaceful revolution, a revolution of ideas, a revolution of creation.  The twenty-first century enlightenment. A global movement to create a  new age of tolerance and understanding, empathy and respect. An age of  unfettered technological development. An age of sharing ideas and  cooperation. An age of artistic and personal expression. We can choose  to use new technology for radical positive change or let it be used  against us. We can choose to keep the internet free, keep channels of  communication open and dig new tunnels into those places where  information is still guarded. Or we can let it all close in around us.  As we move in to new digital worlds, we must acknowledge the need for  honest information and free expression. We must fight to keep the  internet open as a marketplace of ideas where all are seated as equals.  We must defend our freedoms from those who would seek to control us. We  must fight for those who do not yet have a voice. Keep telling your  story.  All must be heard.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.anonnews.org/?p=press&amp;a=item&amp;i=619"><em>- Anonymous</em></a></p>
]]></description><link>/2011/03/open-letter-to-the-world/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2011/03/open-letter-to-the-world/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[anonymous]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>