<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[undefined - Dietrich Ayala]]></title><description><![CDATA[Working towards true user agency through a distributed web.]]></description><link>/</link><generator>Ghost</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 02:32:49 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tag/undefined/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA["Bert Wilson, from Bert's World of Little Known Facts"]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>&quot;Ratio of the length of toilet paper used annually in the US to the distance between Earth to Uranus : 1:1 &quot;<a href="">Link</a>  </p>
]]></description><link>/2002/03/bert-wilson-from-berts-world-of-little-known-facts/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2002/03/bert-wilson-from-berts-world-of-little-known-facts/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[quotes]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2002 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA["David McCusker, on writing."]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>&quot;(I&#39;m much happier being able to write for a public mode.) I don&#39;t think my opinion is worth enough for private ideas. But sharing can make marginal notions almost worthwhile.&quot;<a href="">Link</a>  </p>
]]></description><link>/2002/03/david-mccusker-on-writing/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2002/03/david-mccusker-on-writing/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[quotes]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2002 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA["John Robb of Userland Software, on Pessimism"]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>&quot;No sense being pessimistic. It wouldn&#39;t work anyway.&quot;<a href="">Link</a>  </p>
]]></description><link>/2002/03/john-robb-of-userland-software-on-pessimism/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2002/03/john-robb-of-userland-software-on-pessimism/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[quotes]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2002 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA["Meg Hourihan (megnut.com) on the Oreilly P2P conference speakers"]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>&quot;One of my favorite expressions so far, gleaned from the &quot;Military Applications for P2P&quot; panel yesterday was decision superiority. The armed forces are always looking to gain decision superiority apparently, and now I want to as well. I think that would be really helpful in most situations.&quot;  </p>
<p>&quot;Another expression used yesterday that I loved came from Cory Doctorow in his &quot;A New Way of Understanding P2P&quot; presentation. He talked about the concept of an imagination proposition, or the idea that people get involved in something simply because it&#39;s interesting. An example he stated was the huge number of people involved in SETI@home vs. P2P projects searching for cures for AIDS or cancer. While the value proposition for an AIDS cure is higher than the search for extraterrestrial life, it&#39;s simply more interesting to people to dedicate their spare CPU cycles to the search for aliens. Imagination proposition.&quot;<a href="">Link</a>  </p>
]]></description><link>/2002/03/meg-hourihan-megnutcom-on-the-oreilly-p2p-conference-speakers/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2002/03/meg-hourihan-megnutcom-on-the-oreilly-p2p-conference-speakers/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[quotes]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2002 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA["Nicholas Lehuen on Schema Validation (xml-dev)"]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>&quot;I still don&#39;t understand why validation is not performed in a SAX filter rather than in parsers. Parsers like Xerces have dramatically grown in size and have performance problem due to the fact that validation is built in the parser.   </p>
<p>To me, parsing and validating are two different activities. They may have  </p>
<p>been integrated for performance reasons of the parsing+validation pipeline,  </p>
<p>but I&#39;d still like to have a clean, high performance parsing pipeline in  </p>
<p>which I could plugin any kind of validators (eg. Sun MSV).  </p>
<p>Take the bug that causes Xerces 2 to dereference and parse schemas even if  </p>
<p>validation is disabled for example. I hope it has been fixed since, but if Xerces 2 was not mixing a lot of APIs and technologies (parsing, validating, building a DTD specific DOMs, etc.) in a monolithic way, the bug would have never appeared in the first place.&quot;<a href="">Link</a>  </p>
]]></description><link>/2002/03/nicholas-lehuen-on-schema-validation-xml-dev/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2002/03/nicholas-lehuen-on-schema-validation-xml-dev/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[quotes]]></category><category><![CDATA[xml]]></category><category><![CDATA[XML]]></category><category><![CDATA[Schemas]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2002 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA["Old Persian proverb"]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Trust in God, but tie your camel.<a href="">Link</a>  </p>
]]></description><link>/2002/03/old-persian-proverb/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2002/03/old-persian-proverb/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[quotes]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2002 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA["Quote from Nicholas Lehuen on xml-dev"]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>&quot;Building for the future does not necessarely mean we must stick to the past.&quot;<a href="http://lists.xml.org/archives/xml-dev/200203/msg00213.html">Link</a>  </p>
]]></description><link>/2002/03/quote-from-nicholas-lehuen-on-xml-dev/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2002/03/quote-from-nicholas-lehuen-on-xml-dev/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[quotes]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2002 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA["Seth (Session 51)"]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Your life, believe it or not, basically, is a simultaneous happening. You merely see it in slow motion. ~ Seth (Sess.51)<a href="">Link</a>  </p>
]]></description><link>/2002/03/seth-session-51/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2002/03/seth-session-51/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[quotes]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2002 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA["Stafano Mazzocchi, ex Cocoon lead developer, on team software development."]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>A wise man once said: &quot;only when you think everyone is equal to you, you become different&quot;   </p>
<p>I came here to Apache thinking that I was different, that I had better ideas, that I could shape things on my own, and I continued to think that until very recently... but I look around and see a bunch of people that I care about, a bunch of people that I consider friends, a community of equal individuals, in all possible senses.   </p>
<p>Only when I saw that I knew what to do: delegate, let go, let others step in, let others understand this by themselves (good software comes out as a byproduct of our path to learn it)   </p>
<p>This is my suggestion for all of you, even for you experienced members: delegation scales the community and a bigger community means more value,   </p>
<p>more fun, more positive energy. But delegation happens only if you trust, if you consider your fellow community mate equal to you.   </p>
<p>When this doesn&#39;t happen, friction develops, bottlenecks arise, positive energy turns into negative one.   </p>
<p>Just think about it and return on it often: you are never far enough from your ego to be safe.<a href="">Link</a>  </p>
]]></description><link>/2002/03/stafano-mazzocchi-ex-cocoon-lead-developer-on-team-software-development/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2002/03/stafano-mazzocchi-ex-cocoon-lead-developer-on-team-software-development/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[quotes]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2002 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA["Thomas L. Friedman: Naked Air"]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Think about it. If everybody flew naked, not only would you never have to worry about the passenger next to you carrying box cutters or exploding shoes, but no religious fundamentalists of any stripe would ever be caught dead flying nude, or in the presence of nude women, and that alone would keep many potential hijackers out of the skies. It&#39;s much more civilized than racial profiling. And I&#39;m sure that it wouldn&#39;t be long before airlines would be offering free dry-cleaning for your clothes while you fly.<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/26/opinion/26FRIE.html">Link</a>  </p>
]]></description><link>/2002/03/thomas-l-friedman-naked-air/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2002/03/thomas-l-friedman-naked-air/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[quotes]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2002 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA["Tim bray, Taxi article on xml.com"]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>&quot;This is serious; whenever you have people sitting around in front of a machine waiting for it to react, you&#39;re practicing bad management, because computers are cheap and people are expensive.&quot;<a href="http://www.xml.com/pub/a/2001/03/14/taxi.html">Link</a>  </p>
]]></description><link>/2002/03/tim-bray-taxi-article-on-xmlcom/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2002/03/tim-bray-taxi-article-on-xmlcom/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[quotes]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2002 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>