<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[undefined - Dietrich Ayala]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internet freedom, the web and Mozilla.]]></description><link>/</link><generator>Ghost</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2018 11:41:28 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tag/undefined/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Open Web Games]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>BarCamp, to re-appropriate David Cross&#39;s magnificent descriptive powers, is like an earthquake wrapped in a hurricane, nestled in a box of tsunamis. I previously blogged about the <a href="http://autonome.wordpress.com/2009/05/08/portland-firefox-developers-meetup/">Portland Firefox Developers</a> group that emerged from BarCampPortland 3. However, there was yet another fantastic birthing there: the <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/openwebgames">Open Web Games group</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://twitter.com/alainbloch">Alain Bloch</a> scheduled a session called Developing Non-Flash Web-based Games. A bunch of people attended, probably three times what would&#39;ve fit in the room it was supposed to be in, so it was held in a row of cubicles, with most people standing.</p>
<p>It was a great discussion, covering <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en/HTML/Canvas">canvas</a>, <a href="http://get.adobe.com/flashplayer/">Flash</a>, <a href="http://blog.vlad1.com/canvas-3d/">Canvas3D</a>, <a href="http://code.google.com/apis/o3d/">O3D</a>, <a href="http://silverlight.net/">Silverlight</a>, <a href="http://unity3d.com/unity-web-player-2.x.html">Unity</a>, <a href="http://jquery.com/">JQuery</a>, iPhone gaming, and a lot of talk about existing Web-based games. Check out the <a href="http://2009.barcampportland.com/notes/ene">notes from the session</a> for logs of the talk. There was a lot of interest in building libraries for different gaming models and interactions, to ease the building of games on the Web.</p>
<p>The talk was way too short, and at the end it was clear there was interest in building a proof-of-concept game using canvas and other HTML5 technologies. So to further that effort, and to continue the brainstorming on building games using the open Web, we created the <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/openwebgames">OpenWebGames</a> group on Google Groups. Join us in finding ways to make the Web more funnerer than ever!</p>
<p>If you&#39;re coming to the <a href="http://opensourcebridge.org/">Open Source Bridge conference</a> in Portland Oregon from June 17-19, the group is getting together to sprint on development of a game at the <a href="http://opensourcebridge.org/wiki/Hacker_Lounge">OSB Hacker Lounge</a>. Even you&#39;re not attending, if you have ideas for a game to sprint on, or want to join in online, <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/openwebgames">join the group</a>!</p>
]]></description><link>/2009/06/open-web-games/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2009/06/open-web-games/index.html</guid><category><![CDATA[canvas]]></category><category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category><category><![CDATA[games]]></category><category><![CDATA[Gaming]]></category><category><![CDATA[html5]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><category><![CDATA[mozilla]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Dietrich Ayala]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2009 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>